<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A voyce from heaven, speaking good words and comfortable words, concerning saints departed. Which words are opened in a sermon preached at South-weal in Essex, 6. September, 1658. At the funeral of that worthy and eminent minister of the Gospel, Mr. Thomas Goodwin. Late pastor there. Hereunto is annexed a relation of many things observable in his life and death. By G.B. preacher of the word at Shenfield in Essex.</title>
            <author>Bownd, George, d. 1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77157</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3888</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E972_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207757</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866791</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866791</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119077</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77157)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119077)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 144:E972[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A voyce from heaven, speaking good words and comfortable words, concerning saints departed. Which words are opened in a sermon preached at South-weal in Essex, 6. September, 1658. At the funeral of that worthy and eminent minister of the Gospel, Mr. Thomas Goodwin. Late pastor there. Hereunto is annexed a relation of many things observable in his life and death. By G.B. preacher of the word at Shenfield in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Bownd, George, d. 1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by S. Griffin, for J. Kirton, at the Kings-Arms, in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "march. 8.th 1658. March. 8."; the 9 in the imprint date has been crossed out and replaced with an "8".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Goodwin, Thomas, d. 1658 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119077:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VOYCE FROM HEAVEN, SPEAKING Good words and Comfortable words, concerning Saints departed. Which words are opened in a SERMON PREACHED At SOUTH-WEAL In <hi>ESSEX,</hi> 6. <hi>September,</hi> 1658.</p>
            <p>At the Funeral of that Worthy and Eminent Miniſter of the Goſpel, Mr. <hi>Thomas Goodwin.</hi> Late Paſtor there.</p>
            <p>Hereunto is annexed a relation of many things ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable in his Life and Death.</p>
            <p>By <hi>G. B.</hi> Preacher of the word at <hi>Shenfield</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Cor. 15.55.</hi>
                  </bibl> O Death, where is thy Sting?</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luk. 14.15.</hi>
                  </bibl> Bleſſed is he that ſhall eat Bread in the Kingdom of God.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>S. Griffin,</hi> for <hi>J. Kirton,</hi> at the <hi>Kings-Arms,</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:119077:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119077:2"/>
            <head>TO The Right Worſhipful Sir <hi>Henry Wright,</hi> Knight and Baronet: And to the Worſhipful Mr. <hi>John Leech</hi> Eſquire, Juſtice of Peace: And to the Good Gentleman, Mr. <hi>Richard Sherbrook:</hi> Together with the reſt of the Inhabitants of <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weal.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured and much Reſpected,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Do here preſent you with a Sermon Preached at the Funeral of your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor: Loth I was to Preach it, not grudging the Service, but wiſhing the work had fallen into better hands; More loth I was to Print it, well knowing that there is nothing in this or any thing of mine, worth Publiſhing to the world: It ſufficeth me, if by private Preaching, I may ſerve God in the place where my lot is caſt, <hi>I dwell among mine own people.</hi> But the urgent importunings both of Miniſters and other Chriſtians have wearyed me,
<pb facs="tcp:119077:3"/>and being not able to withſtand the many Solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citations, I have forced myſelf to ſend abroad this Sermon, which I Dedicate to your ſelves, to whom of right it doth belong: The occaſion of it was the Death of him, who was <hi>your</hi> Paſtor, <hi>your</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, and whoſe Flock and People <hi>yee</hi> ſometime were. It comes to you by way of Dedication, be pleaſed to own it with your Chriſtian Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. It is indeed very plain without any flouriſhings, and therefore can ſcarce expect a welcome for its own ſake: but it tends to keep up the memory of him, whom you ſometime loved and delighted in, you may welcome it for his ſake: and moreover it contains heavenly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, Counſels, which being the Truths of God, you muſt welcome it for Gods ſake, and for the ſake of your own ſouls. It comes out ſomewhat long after the Preaching, and no marvel if it come late, I had much a do to perſwade with my ſelf to let it come at all. Though indeed the hand of the Lord upon me in a ſore ſickneſs, made it much longer than otherwiſe it would have been. It is enlarged beyond what it was when I Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, becauſe the ſtraits of time (we being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nighted and many perſons far from their home) would not ſuffer me to deliver ſcarce one half of
<pb facs="tcp:119077:3"/>what was then intended: I then only delivered the heads: now you have the enlargements upon thoſe heads.</p>
            <p>And Now, <hi>Honoured and Worthy Friends,</hi> give me leave a little to vent the ſorrows of my heart for this great loſs: The blow indeed lights upon you mainly, but not upon you only, but upon the Neighbour-hood alſo, yea the whole Church of God. I have had many ſad Letters ſince his Death bewailing the loſs. If others at a great diſtance be ſo affected, how ſhould you your ſelves much more lay to heart, you may juſtly call your ſelves <hi>Ichabod, Glory is departed:</hi> The Ark is for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent taken from you. God can <hi>Glory over you,</hi> and ſet up the Ark again among you, <hi>Amen,</hi> the Lord grant it! but yet remember you had a <hi>Goodwin</hi> among you, ſome of you, I am perſwaded, being the Seal of his Miniſtry, will remember him as long as you have a day to live. Your Town of <hi>Brentwood</hi> is famous for its, ſituation upon an Hill, but its eminency of late years was much from <hi>Mr. Goodwins</hi> Miniſtry in that place: Your Hill ſeemed to be the Candleſtick, whereon this <hi>burning and ſhining light</hi> was ſet: He was <hi>a Tower, a Beacon,</hi> on this Hill. His monethly Lectures, which the Neighbours round about did partake
<pb facs="tcp:119077:4"/>of, made it as the <hi>Hill of Hermon and Mount Sion diſtilling dewes upon the Valleys round about.</hi> He is now gone and is as <hi>water ſpilt upon the ground, which cannot be gathered up again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though his Perſon be dead, let his doctrines live, yea becauſe he is gone, let them the rather remain; He ſhall Preach to you no more, unleſs it be by his former labours and holy life, by both which, <hi>he being dead yet ſpeaketh;</hi> Mr. Goodwin <hi>ſtill lives</hi> in Weal, <hi>if ye his people ſtand faſt in the Lord:</hi> which that you may do, as alſo be bleſſed with one to ſucceed, who may call home the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called, and <hi>perfect what is lacking in the faith</hi> of others, is and ſhall be the</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Prayer of him who is Your Servant in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> GEORGE BOWND.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119077:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>REVELAT. 14. v. 13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And I heard a voyce from heaven ſaying unto me, Write. Bleſſed are the dead which dye in the Lord from henceforth.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He words which I have read unto you are part of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Preached by an Angel, the third Angel mentioned in this Chapter: That they depend upon the foregoing words,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riora hac refero.</hi> Aret. in loc.</note> and that the voyce from heaven in the Text was uttered by the ſame Angel is the Judgement of a good expoſitor. This Sermon, as it may fitly be called, begins from verſe the 9th. and we may obſerve three things concerning it. 1. The Preacher. 2. The Matter. 3. The Method.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Preacher, <hi>viz.</hi> God by an Angel from Heaven Preaching and Propheſying to <hi>Iohn,</hi> what things ſhould come to paſs in the latter dayes: In what age theſe things were fulfilled, whether in the time of <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> as ſome, or later Preachers, as others, I ſhall not ſpend time to enquire: The Preacher is an Angel from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and though the Lord ordinarily Preach to his Church by men upon earth, yet in ſome extraordinary caſes he preaches by Angels from heaven: Miniſters indeed are called Angels, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.20. and it is no ſmall honour which ariſeth to that office from the name which the Perſons bear, yet though called Angels,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>Pares An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelis.</hi>
               </note> they are inferiour to them which are in heaven: when they come to Heaven; they with other Saints ſhall be Angels fellows, <hi>Luc.</hi> 20.36.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The matter of the Sermon is deſtruction to the wicked both here and hereafter, but Salvation to the Godly, if not in this life, yet certainly hereafter in the life to come, That which this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel Preached is ſuch, as to which the Scripture in the whole tenour of it conſenteth, and is agreeable to the Analogy of Faith: Angels from heaven will Preach, can preach no other: that of <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8. Is the ſuppoſition of an impoſſible caſe, ſay Expoſitors. There be indeed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119077:5"/>Angels that Preach other Doctrines, the Devil and his Angels from Hell in their Inſtruments falſe Teachers upon Earth: There be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Errors among the School-men, though they be called Angelical Doctors: This Angel in the Text is from heaven, and accordingly his doctrines Scriptural, as all heavenly doctrines are.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Method is Doctrine and Uſe: The doctrinal part of this Angels Sermon lies in verſes, 9, 10, 11. Where the poſition is this, that moſt dreadful plagues do attend Antichriſt and his adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents: This poſition is illuſtrated by ſhewing, 1. The Extremity. 2. The Eternity of their miſery.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The extremity, <hi>verſ,</hi> 16. <hi>Drink of the wine of the wrath of God.</hi> There is the wine of Gods love, the conſolations of the Spirit, when the ſoul is led into the wine-ſellar, and there ſtaied with Flagons, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.5. The ſweet preparative for that collation, which Saints ſhall have in heaven, where ſhall eat and drink at Chriſts Table in Chriſts Kingdom, <hi>Luc.</hi> 22.30. But this in the Chapter is the <hi>wine of Gods wrath</hi> like that in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 60.3. <hi>Wine of aſtoniſhment, or wine gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to make them mad.</hi> 'Tis added here without mixture, not allayed with one drop of mercy, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.13. There is indeed fire and brimſtone put into it and mixed with it, but there is little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in this addition, it makes the Cup more dreadful: there ſhall be drinking in Hell, but it is in draughts of brimſtone.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Eternity and laſtingneſs of theſe evils, <hi>the ſmoke of their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſcendeth up for ever and ever; and they have no reſt day nor night:</hi> the evils which betide the wicked in this life, are but the beginnings of ſorrows, the end will be to have no end.</p>
            <p>This is the doctrinal part, the Application follows in a two-fold Uſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By way of Information, ſhewing that Gods end in theſe judgements (next to the taking vengeance on the wicked) is to <hi>try the patience of Saints,</hi> verſ. 12. To try I ſay the conſtancy of their obedience, whether they will hold the Faith of Jeſus in troubleſome times: 'tis eaſie to ſail in a calm Sea, but to encounter raging waves, and tempeſtuous ſtorms, and not to make Shipwrack of Faith, and a good conſcience is the trial of a Chriſtian indeed, one that is not with <hi>Agrippa</hi> almoſt, but altogether: <hi>here is the patience of Saints, here are they that keep the Commandements of God, and the Faith of Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> The wicked are threatned with the Vials of wrath to be poured upon them, but why ſhould this trouble the Saints? they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119077:5"/>the Lamb; how is their patience tried by the judgements inflicted on ſuch as worſhip the Beaſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes it doth, becauſe when ever the wicked are made to drink the Cup of wrath, they will be furious, outragious and exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mad (as the expreſſion was before) which rage will vent it ſelf in bloody perſecuting the Saints, as the Church hath found in all ages by ſad experience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Then there is no difference between good and bad, but it may be as ill with them, who follow the Lamb, as who worſhip the beaſt; then we may ſay with the profane ones in <hi>Malachy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tros Tyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſque mihi nullo diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> 
               <hi>what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit is it to ſerve God?</hi> will God ſuffer the righteous to be ſlain with the wicked, and the <hi>righteous to be as the wicked?</hi> Gen. 18.25.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That be far from the Lord, and therefore if we mark what follows, we ſhall be able to diſcern between the righteous and the wicked, him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not; the worſt that can befall them is the loſs of this preſent life, Perſecutors can but kill the body, and therefore,</p>
            <p>Secondly, by way of conſolation he ſheweth there is no cauſe why believers ſhould be diſmayed at the troubles, which may betide them in this preſent life: for while Tyrants make havock of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, God cares for the ſoul and eternal ſalvation; if they dye by the hand of the wicked, this is the hardeſt meaſure that can be meted to them, this is the heavieſt ſhock which can befall them, and having once undergone this, perfect bleſſedneſs preſently followes, <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord.</hi> Having thus cleared the coherence, the Text, as you ſee, is the very Uſe of conſolation, and it affords ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great comfort to the people of God: eſpecially if we conſider what goes before, and what follows after, for from both it receives both light and ſtrength, and comes to the Church (as the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> to <hi>Solomon</hi>) attended with a very great train.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that which goes before is <hi>a voyce from heaven ſaying Write.</hi> Though every paſſage in this Angels Sermon need be attended to, yet this eſpecially: therefore <hi>a voyce from heaven</hi> alarms us to attention; and though every ſentence be worth noting, writing, ſetting down, yet this above all: therefore <hi>write.</hi> This word <hi>write,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nihil hie ſine pondere &amp; menſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>râ.</note> is as a finger pointing to ſome excellent matter, 'tis a Star ſet by it, and a light held over it, that none may paſs by without diligent weighing it, and though there be nothing in Scripture, but hath its weight and worth, yet ſome truths are moſt diligently to be heeded, even above others. Divines obſerve, that the word <hi>behold</hi> in the beginning of a ſentence,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119077:6"/>and <hi>Selah</hi> in the end of a ſentence, do ſhew, that thoſe are remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſentences: ſo we may ſay of this word write. All Scriptures are alike true, but ſome are to be noted by us in a principal manner.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That which follows after is the Spirits ſanction, <hi>yea ſaith the Spirit,</hi> and as if the bare teſtimony of the Spirit were not enough to carry the matter, there are two reaſons annexed.</p>
            <p>Firſt is, when death comes, they <hi>reſt from their labours.</hi> The wicked have all their comfort here, <hi>Luc.</hi> 16. <hi>Son, remember thou haſt had thy good things;</hi> ſo the Godly have all their ſorrows here. 'Tis the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſome, that Chriſts weeping over <hi>Lazarus,</hi> Joh. 11. was not becauſe he was dead, but becauſe he was to be raiſed to this trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome life again, for ſuch is this life at the beſt to the Godly: had it been <hi>Samuel</hi> indeed, he might well ſay, <hi>why haſt thou diſquieted me?</hi> 1 Sam. 28.15. The Godly in this life have labours in common with others <hi>(ſufficient to every ones day is the evill thereof)</hi> but beſides, they have troubles, which the wicked feel not, Satans winnowings, buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetings, a law in their members warring againſt the law of their mind: But death ſtills and quiets all, 'tis to them the ſilent houſe and place of reſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Impii judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabuntur ſecundùm &amp; propter opera ſua; pii verò ſecundùm fidei opera, ſed non propter opera.</note> The ſecond reaſon is, <hi>their works follow,</hi> in happy rewards, he means their good works. The beſt of Gods Children have their evill works, but they are waſhed away in the blood of Jeſus, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot follow them; their good works do follow through free grace in glorious rewards: they ſhall be rewarded <hi>according to their works, though not for their works;</hi> and thus they follow. The works of wicked men follow, but 'tis in everlaſting puniſhments: they ſhall be rewarded <hi>both according to, and alſo for their works;</hi> and thus they follow through divine Juſtice.</p>
            <p>Having thus opened the words, I might draw from them many uſeful obſervations, but becauſe the time will not allow the handling of them, I ſhall not ſo much as name them; there is one point only, which I intend to ſpeak to, and it is that wherein the marrow and ſweetneſs of the conſolation lies: I ſhall lay it down almoſt in the very words of the Text, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>They who dye in the Lord, ſhall certainly be bleſſed when they dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Point is ſo clearly held forth in the Text, that I need not look out for other Scriptures to confirm it, but I ſhall gain the time in ſparing what may beſpared: That which I intend is, firſt to ſpeak to it by way of Explication, and ſecondly by way of Application.</p>
            <p>There be three things needful to be explained, 1. Who may be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119077:6"/>ſaid to die in the Lord, 2. What the bleſſedneſſe is, which they who die in the Lord ſhall have. 3. The time, when they ſhall have it.</p>
            <p n="1">I. For the explaining of the firſt, who may be ſaid to die in the Lord, I ſhall take notice of two opinions about it, and then lay down a third, which I conceive holds forth the true meaning of this phraſe, <hi>to die in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt therefore, ſome widen the Phraſe too much, as if it did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend and take in all thoſe, who having lived profeſſors of the true God and true Religion, die holding this profeſſion. Theſe make every formal profeſſion, though abſtracted from the power of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, enough to carry a perſon to Heaven, making <hi>the Gate wide, which Chriſt ſaith,</hi> Matthew 7. <hi>is narrow.</hi> Let Men profeſſe the true Religion, that is, be Chriſtians, not Jews, Turks, at leaſt be Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, not Papiſts; let them be Orthodox in Judgement, and not groſly ſinful in life; let them but keep their Church, hear, pray, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, and walk in a round of duties: theſe ſhall be ſaved when they die. This is the opinion of ſome. This hath proved a ſpreading leaven, and it is no wonder to ſee the Aſſertors of ſuch Doctrine, draw ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Diſciples after them, it is ſo pleaſing, and who almoſt would not trade for Heaven, if it may be purchaſed at ſo eaſie a rate? 'Tis a Matchiavilian axiome, that to <hi>ſeem religious is profitable, but to be religious is troubleſom;</hi> Now if that be enough to make one religious, which was laid down before, I pray what great trouble is it? hear a few Sermons, mumble over a few prayers; they may do this and yet <hi>live at eaſe in Syon.</hi> 'Tis uſually ſaid to the reproach of zealous profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors that ſome make more a do, than they need, Maſter favour thy ſelf, be not righteous over-much, leſſe will ſerve thy turn: But now if <hi>the Kingdom of God conſiſt not in word but in power; If many may ſtrive to enter into Heaven, and yet not be able;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.20 Lu. 13.23. Mat. 11.12</note> 
               <hi>If Heaven muſt be ſtormed and taken by violence:</hi> then ſurely every formal, ſlight ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of God, will not ſerve the turn, nor ſuffice to arrive to that bleſſedneſſe promiſed in the Text, to ſuch as die in the Lord. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Goſpellers may <hi>ſeem to live in the Lord,</hi> Rev: 3.1. <hi>Have a name to live,</hi> and ſo they may <hi>ſeem and but ſeem</hi> to themſelves, and ſome others, to die in the Lord, but the hoped-for bleſſedneſſe, <hi>where, where will it be?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Some on the other extreme,
<note place="margin">Apellabo Martyrem &amp; praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabo ſatis.</note> narrow the ſenſe of this Phraſe too much, limiting and reſtraining it to thoſe onely who die Martyrs, ſealing the truth with their blood. Martyrdom indeed is a piece of ſervice tending greatly to the honour of God, and hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119077:7"/>been honourably remembred by the Saints, and will be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly rewarded from the Lord; Theſe indeed are meant in the Text, yea, chiefly and eminently, but not excluding others who die in the Lord, though they die not Martyrs. Many Expoſitors might be quoted who underſtand it of all the godly, thoſe who die in their beds, as well as thoſe who die at the ſtake; <hi>Peter</hi> was crucified, and dying in the Lord was bleſſed;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Beatus eſt</hi> Petrus, <hi>dum cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figitur, ſed non minùs eſt beatus</hi> Johannes, <hi>dum in le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto moric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ur, uterque enim, &amp;c.</hi> Aret. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi gemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get vocem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>John</hi> dyed in his bed, but yet dying in the Lord was bleſſed. We read <hi>Pſalm</hi> 116.15. <hi>That the death of the Saints is precious in the ſight of the Lord,</hi> not this or that death for kind, but in general whatſoever death they die; and the Original is emphatical, intimating that the Prophet doth not aſſign it and limit it to any one kind of death, but to whatſoever kind of death; And thus ſome Tranſlations render it: And though <hi>Beza</hi> doth tranſlate it as if it pertained onely to Martyrs, yet the phraſe doth not neceſſarily import ſo much, as Doct. <hi>Fulke</hi> ſheweth in his confutation of the Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Tranſlation: were it meant only of Martyrs, the verſe would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther run thus, <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which are killed or ſlain for the Lord, or for the Lords cauſe;</hi> Now many <hi>die in the Lord,</hi> who do not thus <hi>die for the Lord;</hi> as poſſibly ſome may ſeem to die for the Lord, who do not yet ſo much as die in the Lord. The Apoſtle in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. Speaks of ſome,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> who <hi>give their body to be burned,</hi> and yet have not charity, <hi>viz.</hi> any work of ſaving grace, by a Synecdoche; The firſt Martyrs were Innocents, and ſuch ſhould all Martyrs be, but that all be not ſo, the Apoſtle himſelf intimates; and if this be the meaning of <hi>dying in the Lord,</hi> then they are all bleſſed, which the Apoſtle will not affirm, but rather deny. But to conclude this, we may ſay, in ſome ſenſe, all that dye in the Lord die for the Lord, <hi>viz.</hi> as the Pſalmiſt, <hi>For thy ſake are we killed all the day long,</hi> that is, we are lyable to troubles and perſecutions, more or leſs all Saints meet with them, even they who have the peaceableſt lives and moſt quiet deaths; But this is not the reſtrained ſenſe before, which relates only to ſuch as ſhall be violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly killed and murthered in the cauſe of Chriſt; therefore,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If we would know who they be, which are ſaid to die in the Lord, we muſt mark the phraſe and manner of expreſſion, which is very frequent and obvious in Scripture, <hi>viz.</hi> Some perſons are ſaid <hi>to be in the Lord, in Chriſt,</hi> when others are ſaid again, not to be in Chriſt; now ſuch as are thus <hi>in Chriſt, ſhall be bleſſed when they die.</hi> The Scripture, I ſay, ſpeaks often, that ſome are in Chriſt (who is the Chriſtians Lord, according to thoſe expreſſions, the Lords day, the Lords table,) See <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.7. <hi>They were in Chriſt before me,</hi> and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119077:7"/>Verſe 11. Them of the Houſhold of <hi>Narciſſus, which are in the Lord, or in the Lord Chriſt,</hi> Thus 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Paul</hi> writes to the Church, <hi>which is in God, and in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Now theſe phraſes denote that bleſſed and heavenly union, which beleevers have with the Father and the Son, through the Spirit. 'Tis hard to declare and open what this union is, it is eaſier to ſay, what it is not, than what it is: It is uſually for diſtinction ſake called <hi>mystical,</hi> mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 1. That it is real, not putative and imaginary, 2. Spiritual; it is ſo real, that the Scripture ſpeaks as if the beleever had a ſubſiſtence in the Deity, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.14. <hi>We are made partakers of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>if we hold the beginning of our Confidence;</hi> The word which is tranſlated <hi>Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> ſignifies <hi>Subſiſtence.</hi> This and ſome other Scripture-expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions have made ſome ſpeak a great deal too high, ſaying, beleevers are <hi>deified,</hi> and ſome in our dayes blaſphemouſly, ſaying, beleevers are <hi>God-ded in God,</hi> and <hi>Chriſted in Chriſt.</hi> I do acknowledge it is a moſt tranſcendent priviledge for a poor ſinful creature to be united to the eternal Son of God, but what ever this priviledge is, we are to look upon it as a very great myſtery,
<note place="margin">Chriſtiani eſſe eſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe.</note> the perfect knowledge whereof is reſerved for Heaven. Well, ſo it is undeniably, beleevers are in Chriſt, united to Chriſt, yea all Beleevers; this union is eſſential to a beleevers being, it is that which conſtitutes a beleever; It is a ſtrong union, which nothing can diſſolve; it is not poſſible that theſe liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and tyes by which the eternal Son of God, and a poor belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver are knit together, ſhould ever be broken; See <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.35. <hi>Who ſhall ſeparate?</hi> ſo we may ſay, <hi>what</hi> ſhall ſeparate? for the Apoſtles in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction is of <hi>things,</hi> as well as of <hi>perſons:</hi> ſurely if any thing could do it, then Death is the liklieſt, but Death cannot, Verſe 38. Death ſeparates a Man and his eſtate, a Man and his relations, <hi>(bury my dead out of my ſight,)</hi> yea, Death breaks the union of Soul and Body, but not of the Soul and Chriſt; no nor yet of the Body and Chriſt, for that part which ſleeps, which is the Body, <hi>ſleeps in Jeſus,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.14. This union out-lives Death: It is with a beleever dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as with Chriſt dying, Death broke not the Hypoſtatical union between divine and humane nature in Chriſt: though it diſunited Soul and Body (his death being a true death) yet not God and Man in Chriſt; So Death disjoynes not a beleever and Chriſt, though it disjoyn all other things.</p>
            <p>Now then the meaning of the phraſe may be clear. Even that they who are in the Lord Chriſt, that is, united to him, while they live, ſhall be bleſſed when they die; they were in the Lord
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119077:8"/>whiles they lived, &amp; ſtill remain in the Lord, though they dy, therefore certainly ſhall be bleſſed; They die, and ſo are not in the world, they die, and ſo are not in the Body; but for all this, they are in Chriſt, <hi>though they ſleep, it is in Jeſus;</hi> thus we read of the <hi>dead in Chriſt,</hi> 1 Theſ. 4.16. Such as were in Chriſt when they dyed, and thoſe Saints, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13. <hi>Dyed in Faith,</hi> which is all one with the phraſe now before us, for by Faith we are united to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This might ſuffice for the opening of the firſt particular, who they are that may be ſaid to die in the Lord; but before I paſs this, it may not be impertinent nor uſeleſs to take notice of one phraſe, which comes very near this, but is not the ſame, <hi>Romans</hi> 14.8. We read of a <hi>dying to the Lord;</hi> There is a <hi>dying in the Lord,</hi> as in the Text, and a <hi>dying to the Lord,</hi> as in that place to the <hi>Romans; Dying in the Lord</hi> reſpects our habitual eſtate, being ſuch as are united to Chriſt, but <hi>Dying to the Lord,</hi> refers to our actual deportment in the great work of dying. To dying in the Lord it ſufficeth to be true belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, truly engrafted into Chriſt. Now dying to the Lord requires the exerting and putting forth ſome acts of Faith, which are Four.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When Death comes, to ſee the hand of the Lord in it, not ſo much the malignity of the diſeaſe, confluence of bad humours, or what ever may be of the ſecond cauſes: the eye of Faith ſtill looks unto the Lord; Life is of his giving, and Death is of his ſending: our undoings are the Lords doings. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 46.8. <hi>See what deſolations the Lord hath wrought,</hi> whether national or perſonal, in the earth, or in the houſe and family, it is the Lord, he ſingles out particular perſons: Death is as the caſting of the lot. <hi>The lot is caſt into the lap, but the diſpoſing is from the Lord.</hi> The lot is caſt, and ſuch a Tribe taken, then ſuch a Family, then ſuch a perſon, perhaps <hi>Jonathan</hi> a young Man, a good Man is taken: ſo the lot is caſt, ſuch a Pariſh, ſuch a Family, ſuch a perſon, and ſtill the diſpoſing is from the Lord. <hi>'Tis not the drawing a bow at a venture,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 22 34. 2 King. 9.5.</note> but every Arrow is levelled and hath its particular errand, as the Prophet ſaid to <hi>John, I have an Errand to thee O Captain:</hi> This is to die to the Lord, to ſee the Lord comming to our particular ſelves, and ſaying as to <hi>Aaron, Come up and die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To ſubmit willingly to his hand, and to all thoſe diſeaſes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, as by <hi>Axes and Hammers,</hi> he is pleaſed to demoliſh thy Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: yea to ſubmit cheerfully, and welcome death as a meſſenger, that bringeth good tidings. Welcome fire and faggot, ſaid ſome of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119077:8"/>the Martyrs, they imbraced and kiſſed the ſtake, Oh how cheerful were they! How apt are we to bemoan our ſelves, when tidings of death come, as if ſome dreadful evil were upon us; though indeed 'tis a very childiſh thing, children cry when they ſhould be had to bed; Dying to a believer is but <hi>a going to bed,</hi> Iſai. 57.2. To dye to the Lord is willingly to ſubmit, ſaying, if the Lord pleaſe, he can turn my captivity, and rebuke ſickneſs, and ſend health: If he ſay, he hath no pleaſure in me, in my life, breath, temporal being, <hi>here am I, let him do what ſeemeth him good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Whiles under his hand, to lye breathing out thy laſt breath ſweetly to his glory, to lye bleſſing God, to lye calling upon others to love God and to get into Chriſt; Not only not to be moved by the pains of ſickneſs, and pangs of death to do or ſpeak any thing to the diſhonour of God, but to open our mouth to his glory, and the ſhewing forth his praiſe: <hi>God hath made death to work for a believers good, let them endeavour it may work for his glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. To give glory to God in a firm belief, that the promiſe of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life and ſalvation ſhall now be made good to them, expecting bleſſedneſs <hi>immediately</hi> upon the diſſolution; yea to look beyond the grave and mouldring duſt, unto the reſurrection of the body, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſured that it ſhall riſe a glorious body, death being but the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down of a ſmoaky Cottage, that it may be built a ſtately Palace: as the Southſayers ſaid upon the burning of the Capitol by lightning, the Gods did ſuffer it to be, that it might be built better, and more gloriouſly. Now theſe are the actings of faith required in him who would dye to the Lord.</p>
            <p>Now a Perſon may dye in the Lord and be bleſſed, who yet doth not thus dye to the Lord: for theſe actings may be ſuſpended, either 1. Through our inadvertency, not conſidering what duty is incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent upon us to glorifie God in dying. 2. Through violence of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, depriving or at leaſt dulling and ſtupifying the memory, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding &amp; reaſon, which are neceſſarily required to theſe actings. 3. By ſome fit of deſertion, whereby we come to doubt of our evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, which alone can make us cheerfully to ſubmit, <hi>Lord now let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thou thy ſervant depart in peace,</hi> now, and not till now, becauſe <hi>now mine eyes have ſeen thy Salvation.</hi> And thus I have done with the firſt thing, which needed to be explained, <hi>who they be,</hi> that are ſaid to dye in the Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">II. I ſhall now ſpeak to the ſecond, <hi>what that bleſſedneſs is,</hi> which they who dye in the Lord ſhall have: This is an hard thing,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119077:9"/>if not impoſſible to do, the Scripture ſpeaks of it as that which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible, unutterable. See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4. <hi>Paul</hi> rapt up into heaven heard words unſpeakable,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>which it is not poſſible for a man to utter:</hi> yea which is more, <hi>unconceivable,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.9. it <hi>hath not entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heart of man.</hi> 'Tis in vain to expect that it ſhould be ſpoken with the Tongue, which cannot be conceived by the heart: As ſoon may the Earth and Sea be put into a Pot, as the bliſs of glorified Saints into the underſtanding; as ſoon may you hold the whole earth in the hollow of the hand, as comprehend heaven in the heart.</p>
            <p>Much hath been ſpoken and written concerning it, doubtleſs to the great chearing of the hearts of Saints, inſomuch that ſome have been raviſhed with the newes of it, that they have in a kind of impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiency been weary of life, and longed for death, ſaying, <hi>come Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, come quickly;</hi> yet I believe, that when a Saint comes to heaven, he will ſay in the words of the Queen of <hi>Sheba,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 10 6, 7.</note> It was a true report that I heard upon earth of heavens glory, but behold <hi>the half was not told me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle in the place before deſcribes it Negatively, <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, &amp;c.</hi> The eye hath ſeen much, the ear hath heard more than ever the eye ſaw, and the heart of man can conceive more than ever the eye ſaw, or ear heard; yet the heart cannot conceive this. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the full and perfect knowledge of this bleſſedneſs is only to thoſe Saints who are comprehenders of it: The blind man may ſay much of light, but nothing comparably to him who beholds the light; much may be ſaid of the ſweetneſs of honey by what is reported of it, but it is nothing to what may be ſaid from the taſting and eating of it. See 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.2. <hi>it doth not yet appear what we ſhall be,</hi> or what glory we ſhall have, till we come to ſee this light, and eat of this honey. I might therefore ſhut up this part in ſilence, wiſhing you to wait till this glory ſhall be fully revealed; but becauſe ſomething may be expected upon the method before laid down, it being one of the three things promiſed to be explained, and beſides, much is ſaid of it in the Scripture to the unſpeakable conſolation of believers, making them bear up and be of good chear under preſent evils, whereof this life is full, whiles they have <hi>an eye to the recompence of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi> I ſhall therefore as the Lord ſhall enable me, give you a brief collection of what is held forth in Scripture concerning this bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>I cannot <hi>go round about Sion and tell all the Towers,</hi> may I at leaſt but point out ſome; The Iſraelites rejoyced but to ſee ſome cluſters
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119077:9"/>from <hi>Canaan,</hi> and it may refreſh our hearts whileſt we behold ſome parts or pieces of this glory laid down before us: They waited for Gods time to take poſſeſſion of that earthly <hi>Canaan</hi> and ſo muſt we, 'tis but tarry till death comes; Death will put us in poſſeſſion of the heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> then it ſhall be ſaid to Saints, as to <hi>Abraham,</hi> Geneſis 13.17. <hi>Ariſe, walk through the Land in the length and breadth of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beleevers ſhall be bleſſed when they die, but wherein doth this bleſſedneſſe conſiſts? I Anſwer to the making up of bleſſedneſſe, it is required, 1. That it be full, 2. That it be laſting. Fulneſſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, 1. The abſence of all evil, 2. The preſence of all good.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then Saints dying are out of the reach and danger of evill,
<note place="margin">Praſtat non eſſe, quàm miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſſe.</note> of what may be called evil, even the very appearance of evil: Though there were no good in Heaven, yet it is very conſiderable that there is no evil: Now evil is two fold, 1. Of ſin, 2. of puniſhment, but neither is in Heaven.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is no ſin there, this is the grand evil, a poyſonous weed that growes every where but in Heaven. 'Tis ſaid that no venemous thing will live in <hi>Ireland,</hi> I am ſure it is true of heaven. This weed took rooting in paradiſe, but it was the earthly Paradiſe and not the heavenly, whereof Chriſt ſpeaks, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.43. and whereof St. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſpeaks, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4. The beſt of Saints carry ſin about with them: one need not tell them ſo, they know it to the great grief of their heart, it being that which often fetcheth water from their eyes, and blood from their Souls; Hearken but to their Cloſet doors, and you ſhall hear ſad complaints againſt it, and mourning over it: This is that ſtone tyed to the birds legg,
<note place="margin">Anſelm.</note> (as one well reſembles it upon ſeeing boys play) which pulleth it down when it attempts to fly aloft. This is that <hi>Pharaoh</hi> which keeps Gods <hi>Iſrael</hi> in bondage, and hinders from ſerving God as they ſhould and as they would. There is indeed a principle of grace in beleevers, and there is alſo a body of ſin, and in this reſpect they are like to the tribe of <hi>Manaſſe,</hi> half in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> &amp; half on the other ſide <hi>Jordan.</hi> But death will convey them into the heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3.5:</note> and the <hi>Jordan</hi> of ſin ſhall be quite dryed up; may not this be one reaſon why the Apoſtle calls ſins <hi>our members which are upon earth,</hi> members, becauſe of the dear love we are apt to bear to them, they are as dear as the members of our body, as an eye and hand: and <hi>earthly,</hi> becauſe they ſhall not be in Heaven. Theſe ſins by the power of grace are mortified in Saints whiles they are upon earth, but in Heaven they ſhall be nullified, there ſhall not be an
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119077:10"/>
               <hi>hoof left behind.</hi> Here they are <hi>caſt down,</hi> there they ſhall be <hi>caſt out.</hi> The Lord Jeſus will ſay to ſin, that foul Spirit, as <hi>Mark</hi> 9.25. <hi>Come out and enter no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well then admit this, there ſhall be no corruption within, I may add farther no fear of any temptation from without, whether of the Devil or from the World.</p>
            <p>What can Satan do? The Devil without us could not harm us, were it not for the Devil within us: he could do nothing upon Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 14.30. Becauſe he was without ſin, he <hi>found nothing in him</hi> to faſten his temptations to; If he do ſtrike, 'tis as nothing, ſo long as there is no tinder to catch: But beſides I believe, though he goeth to and fro in the earth, that Heaven is none of his walk, none of his circuit, it is not in his commiſſion, or rather permiſſion, Add, what can the World do to them who are gon out of the World? Before <hi>they were not of the World,</hi> now they are not <hi>in the World;</hi> The World here as the Ivy, twiſting about the tree ſucks the heart out; It flatters as <hi>Jael</hi> did <hi>Siſera,</hi> Butter and Milk in a Lordly diſh, and ſo nails the temples of the Soul to the ground; but after death there ſhall be no alluring World. The World, and the things of the World, as to them,
<note place="margin">Angeli non habent ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta.</note> ſhall be no more: <hi>There is no device in the grave,</hi> no trading, no tilling, no ſhops, no farms or cattel, we ſhall be as the Angels, who are not combred with theſe things, There as <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.1. <hi>The Moon ſhall be under our Feet,</hi> we ſhall have as little eſteem of theſe ſublinary things, as the duſt under our Feet. Thus we have the firſt branch of the negative part, Saints ſhall be bleſſed at death, becauſe they ſhall not be infected with the evil of ſin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. After death there ſhall be, as no ſinning ſo no ſuffering; this neceſſarily follows, for take away the cauſe, and the effect will ceaſe, <hi>there ſhall be no complaining in thoſe ſtreets,</hi> and therefore bleſſed, for I may apply the words of the Pſalmiſt,
<note place="margin">Pſalm 144.14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>Happy are the people that are in ſuch a caſe:</hi> hereupon earth is nothing but <hi>Alaſs, wo is me!</hi> wo worth the day! Not only Hell is full of complaining, but the earth alſo: our dayes here are ful of trouble; Our life is like the Prophets book, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Written within and without, lamentations, mournings and wo: within are Fightings, without are Fears;</hi> We are at no time ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from complaining becauſe of ſin, and it is but ſeldom but that we are mourning becauſe of trouble; which ſorrowful condition of ours upon earth is elegantly ſet forth in that place, <hi>Job</hi> 5.7. <hi>Man is born to trouble, as the sparks fly upward.</hi> Indeed, in Hell is nothing but evil, from one end to the other, It is a ſea of evils, without
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119077:10"/>bank or bottom; On earth are ſome fair days, though many be ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and tempeſtuous,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>a rad</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>elatus fuit.</hi> Iſa. 33.24. Iſa. 35.10.</note> but in Heaven whether Saints go when they die, is no fear of any of theſe things; This is that <hi>Tower whether the righteous ſhall run and be ſafe, or ſet aloft out of the reach of danger,</hi> Prov. 18.10. <hi>There the inhabitants ſhall not ſay, I am ſick, ſorrow and ſighing ſhall fly away;</hi> All evil ſhall be baniſhed many thouſand thouſand miles from the lines of Saints communication. I ſhall ſhut up this part with that comfortable Scripture, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Jeſus delivers from the wrath to come.</hi> If ſaved from <hi>wrath,</hi> then from thoſe evils which are the <hi>effects of wrath,</hi> and where there is no ſin to ſtir up <hi>wrath,</hi> there can be no evil, which is the <hi>conſequence of wrath;</hi> and thus we have the Saints bleſſedneſſe negatively, but now,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Poſitively and affirmitively, to make up bleſſedneſſe, there muſt be the preſence of all good, which brancheth it ſelf into two parts, 1. The perfection of grace and holineſs, 2. The fulneſs of bliſs and happineſs.</p>
            <p n="1">1. After death, when the Children of God come to Heaven they ſhall be made perfectly holy: Heaven is that <hi>Holy Land</hi> whether they are going on Pilgrimage; See 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 3.13. There the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>dwelleth righteouſneſſe,</hi> there is its Manſion-houſe and in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon thereof, here upon earth it is but as in an Inn, or a ſojourner.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Heaven is the <hi>lot</hi> or place alloted to holy ones, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.12. There is no poſſibility for a ſinner to get in thither, heaven gate is ſtrongly guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by holy Angels, ſhould they neglect their truſt, yet God is of purer &amp; clearer eyes then that a ſinner ſhould eſcape him; Yea were it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible a ſinner could ſteal into Heaven, yet he ſhould ſoon be thrown out as the Apoſtatizing Angels were, and as <hi>Adam</hi> was driven out of Paradiſe, and the corrupt Nations beaten out of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and the Man without his wedding garment caſt out of the mariage chamber; Yea further, ſuppoſe a ſinner might be let alone, yet he would ſoon void the place of himſelf, it being not a proper element for him to live in; As ſoon may a fiſh live on dry land, as ſinners who drink in iniquitie as the fiſh drinketh in Water, live in that Holy Land.</p>
            <p>But further, there the people of God ſhall be made <hi>perfect in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> Heb. 12.23. <hi>The Souls of juſt Men ſhall be made perfect.</hi> They are holy in this life, but not perfectly holy; Yea, here they have a <hi>perfect imperfection;</hi> Grace is glory begun, and glory is grace per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected; Grace ſhall not be leſſoned, but heightned and increaſed in glory; Grace ſhall be ſwallowed up of Glory, as the rude draught
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119077:11"/>is when the Picture is finiſhed, and as the Morning light is by the noon-day. See 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2. ſhall be like God, this is in the perfecting of holineſs, which is called our being made like God; God at firſt made Man after his own Image, that is in holineſs, as the Apoſtle ſhews, <hi>Eph</hi> 4.24. Now in Heaven there ſhall be a perfect reſtoring of this image. The expreſſion is full, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.49. <hi>We ſhall bear the image of the heavenly,</hi> but it may be Queried, when ſhall this be? the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is in the following verſe, it ſhall be in the Kingdom of God. While we remain in this fleſh we cannot bear this image, and yet it is true again that Beleevers even in this life do bear this Image, the difficulty is eaſily reſolved, here we have the <hi>truth,</hi> there the <hi>perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of holineſſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the Scripture ſpeaks of true holineſs, or the holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of truth, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.24. There is that which is ſuch in truth, though not in perfecton. And ſurely ſo great will this change be, when a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever ſhall be made perfect, that he will ſeem to be <hi>changed into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Man,</hi> as was ſaid of <hi>Saul,</hi> he would even wonder at himſelf to ſee how he differs from himſelf, what he now is, being a compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hender, and what he was, whiles a Traveler below; Great and wonderful is the change in this life, when of a ſinner one is made a Saint, where yet a ſinful unregenerate part remains, but oh how moſt admirable, when ſhall be made a perfect Saint! in whom is nothing that is called ſin, no appearance of evil, no defect, no blemiſh (as is ſaid of <hi>Abſalon) from the ſole of the foot to the crown of the head.</hi> This change will be in mind, will and affections.</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> In the Mind ſhall be light without any darkneſſe, there ſhall be no miſtakes, no doubtings: here though it be given to the godly to know the myſteries of the Kingdom of God, yet they need pray a prayer for the healing of their ignorances. Truths indeed which are neceſſarily required to be known in order to ſalvation, are plain, ſo that <hi>he who runs may read, the wayfaring Men, though Fools, ſhall not err therein,</hi> Iſa. 35.8. Yet other truths are dark, <hi>making darkneſs their pavilion;</hi> Of theſe the Apoſtle ſpeaks, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. Saying in the Scriptures are <hi>ſome things hard to be underſtood;</hi> Thus the Scriptures are compared to a River, where a Lamb may wade, yet again ſo deep in other places, that an Elephant may be drowned; Such myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs is there in many truths, that the moſt knowing Saints may be called <hi>a generation of ſeekers,</hi> ſeeking more and more to find out the meaning of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which ſhews that there is much darkneſs remaining in their minds; There is Ignorance as well as Knowledge in the beſt, yea, more Ignorance then Knowledge in the beſt, as in the beſt garden
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119077:11"/>are more weeds then flowers; In this ſenſe we muſt allow <hi>new lights.</hi> (not as ſome who call old errors new lights,) but new diſcoveries of what before we knew not, whiles the knowledge of theſe heavenly truths is dropt into us; <hi>Son of Man drop thy word,</hi> by which expreſſion is meant, that our knowledge comes to us by little and little;
<note place="margin">Dies poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior prioris Diſcipulus.</note> Thus the Word of God <hi>is precept upon precept, line upon line, now a little and then a little.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when Saints ſhall come to Heaven, the dark ſide of the cloud ſhall be taken away, they ſhall be of the ſame Intellectual complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſtature as the Angels are; There all doubts ſhall be ſolved,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi</hi> Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therus <hi>cum</hi> Zuinglio <hi>optimè con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venit. in vit.</hi> Geyn.</note> truths cleared, conſciences ſatisfied, controverſies ended. As Satan carried Chriſt upon a Mountain, and in a moment ſhewed him all the glory of the world; So Chriſt at death takes the Soul and carries it to the heavenly <hi>Syon,</hi> and in a moment will ſhew it all the glory and excellent myſtery of divine truths. 'Tis in this caſe as with a dull, yet diligent Scholar, he is continually poring upon his Book, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his Leſſon, and fain would he, but cannot beat it into his head, then comes the Maſter, who by his skill makes it facile to him, and brings him quickly to underſtand it, ſo that even he now wonders at his own dulneſſe; And certainly when a child of God comes to Heaven, he will much wonder at his own dulneſſe to underſtand, ſlowneſs to beleeve. This is the firſt, in Heaven the Mind ſhall be fully and clearly enlightned. Now a word of the other two.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Will ſhall be bowed to a perfect conformity to Gods Will, without any Rebellion, in Heaven the Children of God ſhall be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled perfecty to keep the Commandements of God. No meer Man ſince the fall is able perfectly in this life to keep them, but ſhall be able in another life, becauſe the Will ſhall be brought into perfect conformity to Gods Will, the Authentick and original Copy: here Grace is mixed, ſome Faith, much Unbeleef, ſome conformity,
<note place="margin">Neceſſitas immutabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatis non coactionis: libertas a coactione eſt, eſſentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alis volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietas, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus enim voluntas eſſet nolun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas.</note> much Rebellion; We wear a <hi>linſy welſey Garment</hi> as to our ſpiritual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, but then the Will ſhall be made a <hi>Mountain of holineſs, an habitation of righteouſneſs,</hi> The Will ſhall be ſwallowed up of Gods Will, ſo that we ſhall not be able to ſin, yet no force which is incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the Will, but then ſhall the <hi>day of Gods power</hi> ſhine forth to make the Soul perfectly willing to that which is good, and to that onely, then we ſhall be confirmed in goodneſs and holineſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And laſtly, the Affections ſhall be throughly ſanctified, and freed from all diſorder. The exorbitancy and disobedience of theſe Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons make ſad work here in the moſt gracious Souls, that oft though
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119077:12"/>we <hi>know to do good,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 4.17. Rom. 1.18</note> 
               <hi>yet we do it not,</hi> which becomes ſin, even out of meaſure ſinful: that though we <hi>know the truth, yet we with hold it in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs,</hi> whereby our actions becomes unrighteous in the higheſt degree; Now in Heaven they ſhall quietly comply with and give obedience to right reaſon, they ſhall be as obedient as the <hi>Centuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> Servant, who went and came at his Maſters beck: The Affections are the Souls Officers, but here they oft become proud exactors, but there as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.17. The Lord will make <hi>theſe Officers peace, and theſe exactors righteouſneſſe;</hi> The Affections are the Souls feet, the Souls wings to help the Soul with expedition to do the Will of God, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, whether do they often carry and hurry the Soul? even to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſin with greedineſs, to ruſh into ſin as the Horſe ruſheth into the battail; They are fiery metl'd Horſes, 'tis hard to ſit them, they often caſt their Rider; <hi>Hagar</hi> like, they contend againſt their Miſtreſs, but in Heaven the <hi>bond Woman ſhall be caſt out,</hi> there ſhall be no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mora of a fleſhly part, <hi>The Mountain of the houſe of the Lord ſhall be ſet on the top of all our mountaines;</hi> Grace perfected in glory ſhall <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe againſt the houſe of evil doers, and againſt the help of them that work iniquity,</hi> at our very entring the Heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> this <hi>Jordan,</hi> or ſtream of vile Affections ſhall be dryed up. Thus have I done with one part, which ſhewes wherein the bliſſe of glorified Saints conſiſts, they ſhall have the perfection of grace and holineſſe. Now,</p>
            <p n="2">2. They ſhall have the fulneſs of bliſſe and happineſs; What one ſaid of <hi>England</hi> is very true of Heaven,
<note place="margin">Verè hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arum verè puteus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exhauſtus.</note> 
               <hi>it is a garden of delights,</hi> a fountain of good things which cannot be emptied; It was the ſaying of one of the Popes, who yet went near to have drawn it dry, but it may without queſtion be fitly applyed to Heaven. Surely the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God ſhall live an happy life in Heaven; Thus we read of <hi>eating, and drinking, and feaſting,</hi> it ſhall be with them as with that rich Man, they ſhall <hi>fare delicately every day;</hi> We read 1 <hi>King.</hi> 4.22. What daily proviſion was made for <hi>Solomon,</hi> 30. Meaſures of fine Flower, 60. Meaſures of Meal, 30. Oxen, 100. Sheep, &amp;c. Yet a glorified Saint ſhall infinitly ſurpaſs <hi>Solomon,</hi> when he ſhall come to <hi>ſit down with Abraham, Iſaac and Jacob, in the Kingdom of Heaven, at Gods table.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here in this life a Beleever hath ſweet refreſhments in his or her Souls peace, which cauſeth <hi>joy, that paſſeth <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> joy which others know not of, A ſtranger intermedleth not with his joy, but this is far ſhort of what they ſhall have when they ſhall come to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119077:12"/>ſee God as he is, <hi>The beſt Wine is kept till laſt.</hi> The joy which Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers have in this life, ariſing from their inward peace, is ſaid to be full, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.4. Mr. <hi>Saunders</hi> the Martyr ſeemed ſo full, as if he had ſome to ſpare, ſome to bequeath to his Wife, and therefore in his Letter from Priſon to her, he legacies this to her, who had no mony nor worldly goods to give her: His words are thus ſet down in the Book of Martyrs; <hi>I am merry, and I truſt I ſhall be merry, maugre the teeth of Men and Devils; Riches I have none to endow you with, but the ſweet feeling of the love of God in Chriſt, whereof I thank my God I have a part, that I bequeath to you.</hi> Was not his joy full? Mr. <hi>Bolton</hi> lying on his ſick bed, ſaid to his Friends ſtanding about him, that he was <hi>as full of comfort as his heart could hold.</hi> And truly their joy is full in compariſon of the worlds empty joyes, which are but from the teeth outward, but in reſpect of Heavens joy, it is but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choative and comes far ſhort of it: What is the Morning light to.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 36.8. Cant. 5.4.</note> Noon-day? what is a taſte to a full draught? <hi>to drink of the river of pleaſures?</hi> What is it <hi>to look in at the Key-hole,</hi> to the being let in to the Chamber of the Bridegrom? The manner of expreſſion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.21, 23. Is obſervable, where the <hi>good and faithful Servant is bid to enter into his Maſters joy;</hi> There is not onely ſhewed that it ſhall be a place of joy, but there is hinted the greatneſſe of that joy, ſuch as cannot <hi>enter into him,</hi> but therefore he ſhall <hi>enter into it.</hi> It cannot enter into a Beleever, by <hi>Comprehenſion,</hi> but he ſhall enter into it by <hi>fruition;</hi> yea, there is ſhewed in what meaſure the Beleever ſhall partake of it, he ſhall enter into it, not hear of it, or only ſee it, but go into it, and walk it in the length and breadth thereof.</p>
            <p>And further, if this joy exceed the ſweet ſpiritual joy of Beleevers, no doubt but it far ſurpaſſeth the joy of wicked Men and wordlings: Indeed their joy is often great and full in its kind, <hi>they drink Wine in Bowles, they lie upon beds of Ivory, they chaunt to the ſound of the Viol.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 6.4, 5, 6.</note> I have heard of one who reſolved to ſpend 500 l. to pleaſe his 5. ſenſes, and I have read of another, who provided ponds of ſweet waters to drown himſelf in, after he had ſpent what time of life he might in ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feting &amp; wallowing in ſenſual pleaſures. Now can we think theſe joys may be compared with the joy, bliſſe and happineſſe of Heaven, they are not worthy to be named the ſame day with the ſpiritual joy of Beleevers before ſpoken, which yet as hath been ſhewed comes far ſhort of what ſhall be in glory; Worldly joyes are vain, empty, frothy, thoſe we ſpeak of are full and ſubſtantial; They are ſeeming, painted joyes, they do not reach the heart, nor quiet the heart, at leaſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119077:13"/>give but a light touch, a kind ſalute, and paſs away; but thoſe whereof we ſpeak are laſting and abiding, they refreſh both inward and outward Man, the heart and the fleſh, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 84.2.</p>
            <p>I ſhall here lay down one convincing Argument to prove that the joy which glorified Saints ſhall have, muſt needs go beyond all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pleaſures and joyes whatſoever: take it thus; The higher and greater the mercy is, the greater muſt needs the joy be; Theſe keep pace, and as one riſeth, ſo the other riſeth alſo, the more weight is hung on, the faſter the wheeles move, See <hi>Pſalm</hi> 126.2. <hi>Our mouth was filled with laughter, and our tongue with ſinging.</hi> Now what might cauſe this great joy, <hi>Verſe</hi> 3. <hi>The Lord hath done great things for us,</hi> great Mercies are Ecchoed again with great joyes: Now what greater Mercy can a poor Creature be capable of, than to ſit in heavenly places? If this be the greateſt Mercy, as ſure it is in it ſelf, and in the account of gracious Souls,
<note place="margin">Pſa. 73.24</note> witneſſe their waiting, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven longing, till <hi>afterward</hi> come, when they ſhall be received to glory, then it muſt needs provoke the greateſt joy, like that ſpoken of <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.10. Which ſome expound of Heaven, <hi>they ſhall come to Zion with ſongs, and everlaſting joy ſhall be upon their heads</hi> (the head be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put for the whole Man, as <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.6. And many other places,) the meaning is, they ſhall be all over covered with joy, from top to toe. That which is poured on the Head will run down, and thus the joy of Heaven ſhall be,
<note place="margin">Luc. 6.38.</note> 
               <hi>good meaſure, preſſed down and ſhaken toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and running over.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall cloſe up this ſecond part with one conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by beſides what hath been already ſaid, it may appear, that the life in Heaven and glory ſhall be happy in exceeding great joy, and it is this, <hi>The work of Beleevers in glory, ſhall be in continual praiſing God,</hi> ſinging ſongs to the praiſe of free grace, whereby they are brought to Heaven, whiles others, otherwiſe alike, hewed out of the ſame Rock, digged out of the ſame pit, are yet turned into Hell; Now ſinging is the expreſſion of mirth and joy, as by the buſh hung out, we know there is Wine within, ſinging comes not from an heavy heart. <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.20.</p>
            <p>Some ſay it ſhall be the onely work with which the People of God in Heaven ſhall be wholly taken up, the <hi>Jewes</hi> ſay that the ſacrifice of praiſe or thank-offerings exceeds all other ſacrifices in two things. 1. In the univerſality, being performed by Men and Angels. 2. In the perpetuity, when all other ſacrifices ſhall ceaſe, this ſhall remain, this ſhall out-live all legal ſacrifices, and be the <hi>proper work</hi> of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119077:13"/>bleſſed: when praying ſhall ceaſe, and hearing ceaſe, Yet praiſing and ſinging Hallelujahs ſhall continue; I may apply hither, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 84.4. <hi>Bleſſed are they that dwell in this houſe, they ſhall be ſtill praiſing God; still</hi> or evermore; We have heard what flocking there hath been ſometimes to the Univerſity, to be preſent at a Muſick act; Now in Heaven there ſhall be continual Muſick, ſinging and making melody, continual praiſing; Some think the very forms of words, wherewith glorified Saints ſhall praiſe God, are ſet down in <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Bleſſing, Honour, Glory and Power, be unto him that ſitteth on the Throne, and unto the Lamb, for ever and ever.</hi> And <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.17. <hi>We give thee thanks O Lord God Almighty, which art, and waſt, and art to come.</hi> I have read that holy <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s laſt words were, <hi>Glory be to God from all creatures,</hi> they are as it were the breathings of a Soul in Heaven, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was quite gon from the earth.</p>
            <p>The ſumme of all is this, that Believers ſhall have perfect bliſs and happineſs. They ſhall live in Heaven, where ſhall be pleaſures, mirth, ſinging and rejoycing, above what we are able to expreſs or to conceive. This ſhall ſuffice for the firſt branch of the ſecond part, by way of Explication, They who dye in the Lord are <hi>bleſſed.</hi> Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs muſt be <hi>full,</hi> that is, there muſt be <hi>no evil,</hi> and there muſt be <hi>all good,</hi> the perfection of grace and holineſs, with the fulneſs of bliſs and happineſs: But now,</p>
            <p n="2">2. As it muſt be <hi>full,</hi> ſo it muſt be <hi>laſting</hi> and enduring, and ſo indeed the beſſedneſſe of Saints ſhall be, not onely for a long time, but for ever. It ſhall be Eternal, ſuch as is the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of our Souls, which had a beginning, but ſhall have no end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, called <hi>Eviternity,</hi> to diſtinguiſh from the Eternity of God,
<note place="margin">A parte poſt non a parte ante.</note> who alone is the <hi>firſt and laſt, without beginning, without ending.</hi> This bliſs hath a beginning, <hi>henceforth</hi> ſaith the Text, but ſhall have no ending, it is Eternal. Eternity, at the very naming of it, is enough to amaze our thoughts in ſtudying to know what it is; It is the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of any good thing which makes it a full good; <hi>Soul take thine eaſe, thou haſt goods laid up for many years,</hi> ſaid the rich Man in the goſpel: He glories not ſo much in the abundance of his goods, as in the hope of their continuance. How do Men rejoyce in the purchaſe of an eſtate, becauſe they have that, not by leaſe for term of years, but the Deeds run to them, and their Heirs for ever; Though indeed it is not for ever, but far ſhort of that; For beſides, what may happen in the interim, at the great day all the Evidences ſhall be undoubtedly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119077:14"/>burnt, and it is more than probable from divers Scriptures, the Land alſo, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.6. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.35. 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 36.10, 12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.1. To be ſure, the propriety, in theſe pronouns <hi>Mine</hi> and <hi>Thine,</hi> ſhall ceaſe: Yet the hope Men have of its continuance for ſome long time; doth much content them. <hi>David</hi> took it as a great favour, that God would beſtow a Kingdom upon him, to raiſe him from following the ſheep to be King over <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.18. Yet <hi>Verſe</hi> 19. He ſaith, <hi>This was but a ſmall thing,</hi> that which made the mercy great, was that God had ſpoken of <hi>continuing it for a great while to come;</hi> he adds, <hi>and is this the manner of Man O Lord God?</hi> he ſeems to be much tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported in admiring the continuance of his Mercy, though it were not ſo much to him in perſon, but to his poſterity: Let a thing in it ſelf be never ſo excellent, yet the fear of loſing it, darkens all the excellency of it; Earthly treaſures are therefore leſs to be accounted of becauſe <hi>Thieves may break thorough and ſteal them;</hi> What true content could the rich Man take in his abundance, when once he heard, <hi>This night</hi> all ſhould be gone?
<note place="margin">Corneliam neſcie an faeliciorem talem viru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habuiſſe, an miſeriorem amiſiſſe. Et invito proceſſit veſper O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lympo.</note> 'Tis ſpoken to the humbling of the great ones upon earth, that though they <hi>live like Gods, yet ſhould die like Men;</hi> Though the good thing be great, yet if not laſting, tis not ful: yea, the greatneſs of it, greatens the miſery upon the loſing. When a Scholar hath been reading a good Book, it troubles him to ſee <hi>Finis;</hi> When the people of God have been keeping a day of Prayer in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, it ſaddens them much that they ſhould break off, becauſe the day is done.</p>
            <p>But now the bleſſedneſs of Saints is not onely a great good, as hath been ſhewed, but a laſting good, it ſhall have no end, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.17. <hi>They ſhall be for ever with the Lord,</hi> Rev. 3.12. <hi>He that goeth in ſhall go out no more;</hi> ſome interpret it of a Beleever in this life,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Notat glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae ſtabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem,</hi> Piſc. <hi>in loc.</hi> Iſa. 33.20.</note> to prove no falling from grace, ſome again interpret it of the ſtate of glory. The life of glory is ſuch a life, to which immortality is eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. We read of <hi>life and immortality,</hi> that is to ſay, immortal life; <hi>Heaven is a Tabernacle that ſhall not be taken down, not one of the ſtakes thereof ſhall ever be removed, neither ſhall any of the cords thereof be broken.</hi> The bleſſedneſſe of Beleevers ſhall be eternal: but what is Eternity? I ſhall ſhew you how a learned and holy Divine illuſtrates it to the meaneſt capicity, <hi>Suppoſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the whole World were a Sea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins <hi>on the Creed.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and that every thouſand years expired, a bird muſt carry away or drink up one onely drop of it: in proceſſe of time it will come to paſſe, that this Sea, though very huge, ſhall be dryed up, but
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119077:14"/>yet many thouſand millions of years muſt be paſſed before this can be done. Now if a Man ſhould enjoy happineſſe in Heaven onely for the ſpace of time in which this Sea is drying up, he would think his caſe moſt happy and bleſſed: but behold the Elect ſhall enjoy the Kingdom of Heaven, not onely for that time, but when it is ended they ſhall enjoy it as long again, and when all is done, they ſhall be as far from ending of this their joy, as they were at the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now by what hath been ſaid, we may in ſome meaſure un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, what is that bleſſedneſs which the Saints and Children of God ſhall have; it is great and full, it is alſo laſting, yea, everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which cannot be ſaid of any thing here below; The beſt of the worlds excellencies are fading, and quickly blaſted; No day ſo pleaſant, but ends in a darknight; No Summer ſo fruitful, but ends in a barren Winter; No Body ſo fair, but will be changed by death, from Beauty to Deformity: In the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> they were eating and drinking, but the flood comes and ſweeps them all away; Great mirth was among the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> but their banquetting-houſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes their burying-place; The Monarch of <hi>Babel</hi> whoſe head was of Gold, had the feet of clay:
<note place="margin">Sic tranſit gloria mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di.</note> All the pomp of the world is like <hi>Jonahs</hi> gourd, now flouriſhing and anon fading, there is that worm in the root of all worldly comforts as will blaſt them; But the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and joyes, and comforts of Heaven are not ſuch, they are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity mercies, eternity joyes, eternity comforts: take away the laſtingneſs, or rather everlaſtingneſs, and we blow up Saints hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe. Thus much for the explication of the ſecond thing, <hi>viz.</hi> What that bleſſedneſs is which they who dye in Lord ſhall have. Now a word of the third thing, and ſo I will come to the Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Therefore,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Having ſhewed who they be who dye in Lord, and what the beſſedneſs is that they ſhall have, it remains to ſhew in the third place, when they ſhall be made partakers, and be put in poſſeſſion of it, and that is immediately upon their death, for ſo ſaith the Text, <hi>Henceforth they are bleſſed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> reckons upon his being with Chriſt immediately upon his departure, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. Now Chriſt as he now is, ſo he then was in Heaven, in glory. The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>verted Thief is promiſed he ſhould be received into Paradiſe, as ſoon as he was dead, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.43. This Paradiſe muſt be the heavenly one, for of the earthly one we may ſay, as they of <hi>Moſes</hi> his Body, <hi>no Man knowes where it is to this day.</hi> Again in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.8. We may ſee that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119077:15"/>the Apoſtles expectation was to be preſent with the Lord, as ſoon as he ſhould be once abſent from the body; <hi>Stephens</hi> prayer, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.59. <hi>Lord Jeſus receive my Spirit,</hi> was in vain, or could have no comfortable return, if the Soul doth not at death preſently goe to bleſſedneſs; He doth not pray nor expect that his body ſhould be received to the Lord, but his Soul or Spirit: he knew his body ſhould go to the grave, and he knew alſo his Soul ſhould go to God, according to what Chriſt promiſed, <hi>John</hi> 14.3. <hi>That where he is, there his members ſhould be alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Children of God do not enter into glory preſently at death, they are moſt lamentably deceived, and ſadly fruſtrated in what they conceive ſtrong hopes and go forth in full aſſurance of: Doctor <hi>Preſton</hi> uſed to ſay, <hi>it is but wink and be with God:</hi> the cloſing of the eyes by death, would bring the Soul to the light of life. When <hi>Baſil</hi> that couragious Chriſtian, was threatned with death by the Tyrant, he prayed to God <hi>the Tyrant might not change his intentions, leſt he ſhould loſe his expectation;</hi> he expected to change miſery for glory. <hi>Taylor</hi> the conſtant Martyr, coming within two fields of the place where he was to be burned,
<note place="margin">Mr. Fox <hi>Act and Mon.</hi>
               </note> comforted himſelf that <hi>he was within two ſtiles of his Fathers Houſe,</hi> which was, in his meaning, Heaven. Another Martyr embracing the ſtake ſaid, <hi>This day ſhall I be maried to Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> One of the Antients reproved the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate mourning at the death of godly people thus,
<note place="margin">Cypr.</note> ſaying, <hi>why ſhould we put on black cloaths, when our Friends put on white?</hi> That is the Robes of glory, calledin the <hi>Revelations, the fine linnen of Saints.</hi> I might heap up inſtances of this kind, the conſtant expectation of them that dyed in faith, is at death to enter into their Maſters joy; And though they do not ſay (as I have read of a blaſphemous Monk) <hi>give me eternal life which thou oweſt me,</hi> yet in hope of preſent poſſeſſion of eternal life, which God that cannot lie, hath graciouſly promiſed, they can ſay with <hi>Hilarian, Go forth my Soul, go forth, why trembleſt thou, thou haſt ſerved Chriſt thus many years, and doſt thou now fear death?</hi> I ſhall add further the earneſt deſires &amp; longings after death in ſome of the Children of God, ſurely they promiſed themſelves preſent bleſſedneſſe; Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was not onely willing to die, but did deſire it, yea, vehemently. See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2. <hi>We groan earneſtly;</hi> Some Saints having their hopes raiſed up to the fruition of this glory, have been almoſt impatient, <hi>Come Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, come quickly,</hi> and why are the Chariot wheeles ſo long a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming?
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119077:15"/>they even longed to be (as we may ſay) fingring of it, ſo as never did a rich Heir long more to be in the poſſeſſion of his Lands; They have thought every day ten, every year twenty, ſaying in the words of the Pſamiſt, <hi>Make haste Lord, make haste.</hi> So then I may ſay, and ſo conclude this poynt, if the people of God do not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately at death enjoy bleſſedneſſe, they are the moſt miſerably deluded people of any in the world: Away therefore with that wretched doctrine of the <hi>Souls ſleeping in death,</hi> being altogether Anti-Scriptural, Oh that it might for ever lie dormant and awake no more! It tends much, 1. To the imboldening of ſinners in a way of ſin, See <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.48. The evil Servant that reckoned of his <hi>Maſters delaying his comming,</hi> thereupon grew very bold in more and more ſin. 2. To the ſadning of the hearts of Gods people, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.12. Hope deferred makes the heart ſick. This ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to be ſpoken to the third and laſt thing, and alſo to the whole by way of Explication, the Application follows. In the Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this poynt, I ſhall ſpeak to four uſes. 1. Of Information. 2. Inſtruction. 3. Conſolation. And 4. Exhortation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By way of Information, according to the rule of contraries,
<note place="margin">Oppoſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eadem eſt Scientia</note> if they who are in Chriſt when they die are bleſſed, then thoſe who are not in Chriſt when they die are curſed, upon different accounts; Death hath a different complexion; it is like the Red-ſea, which to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> was a paſſage to <hi>Canaan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aliis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hiculum, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liis Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrum.</note> but to the <hi>Egyptians</hi> a place of drowning to their utter deſturction. To ſuch as are in Chriſt, <hi>the day of their death, is better then the day of their birth,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their encrance into everlaſting joy: but to others it will be the ſaddeſt day that ever came, being the beginning of their ſorrowes. <hi>'Tis appointed for all to die,</hi> in that reſpect all are alike, but it is not appointed for all <hi>to die in the Lord,</hi> in that reſpect there is a great difference of perſons: Some <hi>die in their ſins,</hi> John 8.24. Some are <hi>taken away in their iniquity,</hi> Ezek 33.6. Theſe are curſed when they die, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 9.7. <hi>The wicked ſhall be turned into Hell,</hi> which place ſeemes to be commented upon and explained, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 11.6. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the wicked he ſhall rain ſnares, fire and brimſtone, and an horrible tempeſt: this ſhall be the portion of their cup.</hi> I might here inlar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e upon the ſtate of the damned after death, in the ſame Method as before of the ſtate of the glorified: Before the bright ſide of the Cloud, now the dark ſide. A little briefly.</p>
            <p>When Saints die they are freed from all evil, but when ſinners die,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119077:16"/>they lanch into a Sea of evils. 1. They will find the <hi>abſence of all good.</hi> A godly Mans miſeries terminate with this life, ſo do a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners comforts. I have read of the old <hi>Arcadians,</hi> that they would weep bitterly when the Sun did ſet, fearing it would never riſe more; ſure I am, ſinners dying have cauſe to bemoan themſelves ſadly, for when the Sun of their life is once ſet, it will be perpetual night of darkneſs and miſery: They may weep as thoſe did at <hi>Pauls</hi> parting, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. <hi>ſhall ſee the Face</hi> of comforts no more: they have their portion in this life, and when once they die, they ſhall be alarmed with that memento, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.15. <hi>Remember thou haſt had thy good things,</hi> implying, they ſhall have them no more. 2. There will be to them not onely no good, but <hi>all evil,</hi> as 1. The evil of ſin, there is ſinning in Hell, in Heaven there is none, on earth too much, in Hell nothing elſe. Death cannot kill ſin, but it will live when the ſinner is dead, and therefore <hi>wrath abides for ever,</hi> becauſe ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bides for ever: Wrath will keep pace with ſin; Sin as oyl feeds the fire of Gods Wrath; One ſaid to a Swearer, who would not be reclaimed, prethee ſtay but till thou comeſt to Hell, there ſhalt have thy fill of ſinning and ſwearing. Again, 2.</p>
            <p>There is the evil of puniſhment, therefore <hi>Luke</hi> 16.28. It is called the <hi>place of torment;</hi> as there is a place of bliſs, <hi>John</hi> 14.3. I go ſaith Chriſt <hi>to prepare a place for you;</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> ſay, every Saint ſhall have a ſtar aſſigned him for his Manſion-place, but they have vain conceits in this, as in many other things; but ſurely a certain place there is, it is no <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>biquitary Heaven;</hi> So ſurely there is a place of torment: how great this torment is cannot be known by any, but ſuch as feel it; yet it were well if ſinners would know it before they feel it, thereby to prevent the feeling of it; And certainly 'tis beyond what can be expreſſed; And therefore when we would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort any under the greateſt evils, we ſay, <hi>it is not wrath, it is not Hell;</hi> Chriſt but taſting this, and that but for a few hours, though he were the ſtrong one, compared to a Lyon, yet did ſweat drops of blood; The Scripture expreſſeth it by <hi>weeping, and wailing, and gnaſhing of teeth;</hi> Heavy chear, ſaid Mr. <hi>Latimer,</hi> where weeping and wailing is ſerved up in the firſt courſe, and gnaſhing of teeth in the ſecond:
<note place="margin">Legati do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loris ſunt lachrymae.</note> weeping and gnaſhing, two ſtrange effects of a ſtrange fire, weeping is from burning heat, and gnaſhing of teeth from bitter cold; They ſhall weep, not for their ſin, but for their pain; Again, they ſhall gnaſh, or envy, and grieve at the felicity of the godly, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 112.10. <hi>The wicked ſhall ſee it and be grieved, he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119077:16"/>ſhall gnaſh with his teeth, and melt away.</hi> There ſhall be weeping, ſome conſtitutions on earth cannot weep, but there are none ſuch in Hell; Many on earth ſin and tremble not, but it is not ſo in Hel, their hearts ake under wrath; there is no rejoycing, but trembling, and yelling with the voyce of Dragons, crying out, <hi>woe worth the day that ever they ſinned, Ariſtotle</hi> knew nothing worſe then Death,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but the Scriptures ſhew that Hell is far worſe, the fiery fornace, the <hi>Lake that bnrneth with Fire and Brimſtone,</hi> which will try the ſtrength of the ſtouteſt Sinner, had he <hi>the ſtrength of ſtones, or braſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this add the Adjunct, as the Saints bleſſedneſs ſhall be eternal, ſo will the ſinners miſery be, and this conſideration makes it very diſmal and dreadful; <hi>Iſraels</hi> bondage in <hi>Egypt</hi> was long before it had an end: whiles they were in <hi>Babylon</hi> they were <hi>priſoners in a pit,</hi> but yet they were <hi>Priſoners of hope,</hi> that captivity had an end: <hi>Pharaoh</hi> had ſome reſt from his Plagues, <hi>Exod.</hi> 8.15. <hi>Jobs</hi> conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was extream ſad, who prayes <hi>to be let alone that he may take com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort but a little,</hi> Job 10.20. but it had an end, it was temporal; The ſinners miſery ſhall be eternal. See <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.10. <hi>Shall be tormented day and night for ever and ever.</hi> Hell fire is ſuch as <hi>cannot be quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> Mark 9.44. Though Hell be full of tears, yet theſe floods of tears ſhall not be able to quench this fire. I ſhall add one thing more, and then I ſhall have fully paralleld the miſerable eſtate of them who dye out of Chriſt, with the bleſſed condition of ſuch as dye in the Lord, <hi>viz.</hi> one branch of the former diſcourſe was, that the Saints ſhall enjoy their bliſs preſently at death; So the wicked when they die ſhall be preſently plunged into miſery, it ſhall be deferred no longer; The Scope of the Parable, <hi>Luke</hi> 16. ſhews thus much; though every thing or paſſage in a parable do not prove, or is not argumentative, yet the ſcope carries full and ſtrong proof; Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles are like Knives, the haft will not cut, and the back will not our, but the edge will; The ſcope is as the edge of a Knife, and this ſeemes to be the very ſcope and drift of that Parable, to ſhew all impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſinners what they muſt look for at death, to be tormented as that rich Man was. Further, ſee <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. <hi>After death to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> all muſt come to judgement, and when? preſently <hi>after death;</hi> The godly ſhall be judged, but not condemned, the wicked ſhall be judged and condemned. The Doctrine of <hi>the Souls ſleeping till the reſurrection</hi> is no doubt pleaſing doctrine to ſinners, It would be
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119077:17"/>ſome lightning to them to think of a reprieve to the general judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but the Scripture ſpeaks of a preſent judgement to them, and of their being preſently carried to Hell, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.20. <hi>This night ſhall thy Soul be required,</hi> in the Original it is, this night do they require thy Soul; They, that is, ſay Expoſitors, the Devil and his Angels, Gods inſtruments for executing his wrath upon wicked and ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men.</p>
            <p>Hear this O Sinner, I come to thee with heavy tidings, ſuch as who ever hears it, might make both his ears to tingle. But woe is me! Sinners are even Hell-proof now a dayes; When <hi>Paul</hi> preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of <hi>Judgement to come,</hi> Felix <hi>trembled,</hi> Oh that Sinners would tremble whiles this judgement is future, yet to come, when it is come, the ſtouteſt ſhall tremble: And indeed, better never have been born, then to go out of the world ſinners, as we came into the world. Better be Doggs and Toads, then ſinners and die ſuch: when they die there is an end of their miſery, whereas thou haſt Millions of years to lie in Hell under the wrath of God, not onely while the Sea (before ſpoken of) is drying up, which would be in time, though a long time firſt, but to all eternity, for ever and ever. This is the firſt uſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By way of Inſtruction. Are they bleſſed who die in the Lord? then this teacheth us the true way to true bleſſedneſſe: All would be bleſſed, though many be but <hi>wiſhers</hi> and <hi>woulders</hi> in this very thing of ſo great concernment, having faint, <hi>ſlothful deſires, which will Kill them,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks, that is, leave them ſhort of the good they ſeem to deſire.</p>
            <p>It cannot be denied, but that there is in all ſome deſire after bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs: Though the tree of happineſs be cut down, yet there is (if I may ſo ſpeak) this ſtump left, a deſire after it. <hi>There be many that ſay, who will ſhew us any good?</hi> Pſalm 4.6. And they ſpoken of by the Prophet, <hi>looked for peace,</hi> Jer. 14.19. None ſay, who will ſhew us any evil, none look for trouble and miſery with an expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it; All are for good, peace and bleſſedneſs. <hi>Good Maſter, what ſhall I do to inherit eternal life?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if any be in good earneſt this day, enquiring after the way to happineſs, (ſome make a ſhew of enquiring, as <hi>Pilate</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>What is truth?</hi> which he loved not, nor cared for to know) they may be directed from the Text; They who would be bleſſed, muſt <hi>be in the Lord,</hi> muſt by all means get into Chriſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.6. <hi>I
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119077:17"/>am the way,</hi> ſaith Chriſt:
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The Article in the Original makes it emphatical, <hi>The way, the onely way:</hi> he adds, and <hi>the truth,</hi> this is to beget in our hearts a firm belief that he is the only way. But one may ſay, he is a way indeed, but whether doth this way lead? he adds <hi>the life,</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, <hi>I am in truth the onely way that leads to life</hi> or bleſſedneſſe. Know all Men of a truth, if they be Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, they will be bliſſeleſs, heavenleſs; Tis Chriſt who hath <hi>brought life and immortality to light,</hi> therefore immortal life muſt be by Chriſt. Jeſus Chriſt is that <hi>Ladder</hi> in Jacobs viſion, by which Believers climb up to Heaven; Life was a book ſealed, but Chriſt hath ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ed it; the way of bleſſedneſſe was ſhut up, but Chriſt hath cleared the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, we muſt ſay with the Martyr, <hi>None but Chriſt, None but Chriſt,</hi> Creature righteouſneſs will not open the Door of bleſſedneſs: Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are Creatures, yea, graces are Creatures; Faith it ſelf is no Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; So then if we would be bleſſed, the queſtion which we muſt put to our Souls is this, are we in Chriſt? They who are in the Lord Jeſus ſhall be bleſſed.</p>
            <p>For the tryal of this, take this one concluſion, <hi>If we be in Chriſt, then Chriſt is in us:</hi> As we read of Saints being in Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. So we read of Chriſt being in Saints, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. Take one place more, wherein this mutual inhabitation is expreſſed fully, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.24. <hi>He that keepeth his Commandments dwelleth in him,</hi> that is, in Chriſt, <hi>and he in him,</hi> that is, Chriſt dwelleth in him that keepeth his Commandments. So that one diſcovers the other, <hi>viz.</hi> if we be in Chriſt, then Chriſt is in us.</p>
            <p>Yea, but it may be replied, this is as hard to know as the other; how can Chriſt be in us? he is in Heaven, <hi>him the Heavens muſt contain till, &amp;c.</hi> I anſwer, the Scripture ſhews that though Chriſt be in Heaven, yet he dwells in his people upon earth by his Spirit: and thus in the place laſt quoted, this is made a mark or note of try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, <hi>Hereby we know that he abideth in us, by the Spirit which he hath given us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet ſtill there is not a full reſolution to a conſcience that deſires ſatisfaction. But it may be further queried, how I ſhall know whether I have the Spirit.</p>
            <p>To this I Anſwer, ſome know it by its immediate witneſſe, <hi>the Spirit bearing witneſſe with their Spirits.</hi> Thus <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8:16. 2 Tim. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>I know whom I have believed,</hi> this is an high attainment, not given to all; And therefore I add, others may know it by its argumentative witneſs, the Soul drawing concluſions from the effects, which are ſuch as theſe following.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:119077:18"/>
            <p n="1">1. It is a ſoftening Spirit; Haſt thou the Spirit of Chriſt dwelling in thee? then it hath mollified thy Adamantine heart, thou canſt ſay, my heart by nature is in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>exible, impenetrable, but it is made tender, bowed and ſoftned.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is an enlarging Spirit; Art thou enlarged with <hi>David, to run the way of his Commandments?</hi> This he deſired to do, but could not, till <hi>God inlarged his heart,</hi> Pſalm 119.32. Art thou inlarged in dutie, and in graces? ſtronger in believing, more broken in heart, more frequent and fervent in praying, hearing, receiving, is it thus with thee?
<note place="margin">Sam: 1.5.10.</note> Thus it was with them who have the Spirit: or rather haſt not cauſe to mourn, as <hi>Hannah,</hi> becauſe <hi>her womb was ſhut up,</hi> ſo thou, becauſe thy Soul is ſhut up? Perhaps haſt no pantings after God, and inſtead of being inlarged, thou decayeſt, declineſt, and goeſt down the wind.</p>
            <p n="3">3. 'Tis an enlightning Spirit; The heart naturally is covered with darkneſs, darkneſs that may be felt, but where the Spirit dwells, it makes an <hi>Egypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 1.78, 79.</note> a <hi>Goſhen:</hi> Now hath <hi>the day spring from on high viſited thee, to give light to thy Soul which ſat in darkneſs?</hi> Hath it inlightned thee to know the great evil of ſin, the dreadfulneſſe of offended Juſtice, the preciouſneſs of thy immortal Soul, the ſweetneſs of a pardoned eſtate, the tranſcendent excellency of Chriſt, the Beauty of holineſs?</p>
            <p n="4">4. 'Tis a ſanctifying and cleanſing Spirit; The heart naturally is lamentably ſulled and defiled, the <hi>Conſcience is impure:</hi> The Soul coming out of an unregenerate eſtate,
<note place="margin">Cant. 3.6.</note> is ſaid to <hi>come out of the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs like pillars of ſmoak:</hi> The Soul naturally is a ſmoaky, ſooted, and defiled thing, but when the Spirit comes in, it clenſeth; Now hath God <hi>created in thee a clean heart?</hi> which <hi>David</hi> prayes for, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 51.10. The Spirit is compared to fire; Now fire cleanſeth the Gold from the droſs; hath the Spirit conſumed the droſs of ſin and corruption? 'tis a Spirit of burning, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4.4.</p>
            <p n="5">5. 'Tis a fructifying Spirit; The heart by nature is a <hi>wilderneſs,</hi> as in the <hi>Canticles,</hi> a barren wilderneſs, bearing nothing but bryars and thrones, and no good fruit; Art thou now become fruitful in good works, or rather art thou not <hi>to everie good work reprobate?</hi> I might add</p>
            <p n="6">6. 'Tis a warming Spirit; The heart naturally is key-cold, the conſcience benummed: Is there any ſpiritual heat, holy warmth in thy Soul? is there alwayes ſome of the holy fire burning upon the Altar of thy Soul? The ſum of all is this, if theſe things be not in us, or
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119077:18"/>at leaſt a ſenſe of the want of them, with a mourning for to have them, then the Spirit is not in us, and if the Spirit be not in us, then Chriſt is not in us, and if Chriſt be not in us, then we are not in him, and if we be not in him, we cannot be bleſſed: <hi>They only are bleſſed who are in the Lord;</hi> There is no other way to bleſſedneſs; and thus much for the ſecond uſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By way of Conſolation to all true Beleevers, you are in Chriſt, and you ſhall be bleſſed when you die: 'Tis but waiting a while, till Death, and <hi>henceforth</hi> you ſhall be happy. You perhaps are now miſerable, but you ſhall not alwayes be ſo,
<note place="margin">Pſa. 73.24</note> 
               <hi>afterwards thou wilt receive me to glorie;</hi> Thus that holy Man <hi>Aſaph</hi> comforted himſelf: Can you not live a little upon hope?
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.26. Heb. 10.34.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes eying the recompence of reward could ſuffer rebuke:</hi> Thoſe Worthies calling to mind <hi>the better and enduring ſubſtance, could take joyfully the spoyling of their goods,</hi> and can you bear nothing, ſuffer nothing? True, you have not this glory in poſſeſſion, but you have it in reverſion; Tis as ſure as ſure as may be, the entail cannot be cut off: Chriſt urgeth this as an argument why his Diſciples ſhould forſake all &amp; follow him,
<note place="margin">Matth. 19.28.</note> becauſe they ſhould after <hi>ſit upon thrones of glorie with him;</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> thence preſſeth, they ſhould be contented to ſuffer becauſe <hi>they ſhould be glorified: Ridlie</hi> the Martyr cheered up his fellow, ſaying,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.17.</note> though we have <hi>a bitter break-fast, yet we ſhall have a ſweet Supper,</hi> meaning in glory. From theſe paſſages I may infer to your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, who are Chriſtians indeed, that be your preſent burthens ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo heavy, yet glory, yea, I may ſay, <hi>one half hour in glorie,</hi> will make amends for all: Some perſecutors have been very witty to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent moſt exquiſite torments, yet the hope of bleſſedneſs hath made them to be as nothing; The Martyrs in their undaunted courage, made no more of them then <hi>Sampſon</hi> of the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> withs, or like the <hi>Leviathan</hi> in <hi>Job, Iron is but as ſtraw, and Braſs as rotten wood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 41.27.</note> All their troubles and ſufferings are but light: they are heavy in themſelves, but the weight of glory makes afflictions light. See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17, 18.</p>
            <p>Oh Chriſtians, do but make experiment: when you are apt to droop, and find your Spirit is overwhelmed, run to this as to your <hi>Aqua Vitae</hi> bottle, take but a ſip of it and it will refreſh you: you ſhall be bleſſed, <hi>Write, bleſſed are, &amp;c. Yea ſaith the Spirit; Oh then lift up the Hands which hang down, and the feeble Knees!</hi> There is no Cup ſo bitter, but this will ſweeten it; no Fire ſo hot, but this will ſlack and quench it. I ſay again, do but make experiment; God
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119077:19"/>hath provided many ſupports for his drooping people; but I may ſay as <hi>David</hi> of <hi>Goliahs</hi> ſword, <hi>None like to this,</hi> no ſupport like the remembrance of glory: <hi>One leaf of the tree of life, is better then cluſters of worldly comforts.</hi> Be thy burthen what it will, how heavy ſoever, yet the calling to mind future bleſſedneſs will make it light and eaſie:
<note place="margin">Gen. 21.19.</note> But alaſs, Saints droop, and with <hi>Hagar</hi> are ready to faint, when there is a Well of water by them, but they ſee it not, at leaſt have not skill to draw: The Lord open your eyes as he did hers.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, when ſhall we have this bleſſedneſſe and glory? I Anſwer, at Death you ſhall have it, not now, but afterwards. See <hi>John</hi> 13.36. Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Peter, whither I go, thou canſt not follow me now, but thou ſhalt follow me afterwards:</hi> Chriſt went to Heaven, thither <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould come at length when he dyed. Death is in a ſort a cauſe of this happineſſe, that is, without which it will not be; And indeed, ſee how graciouſly God hath ordered it; Death came as a curſe,
<note place="margin">Mal. 2.22.</note> but it is turned into a bleſſing: God threatneth to the wicked, to <hi>curſe their bleſſings,</hi> and promiſeth to the godly <hi>to bleſs their curſes.</hi> Death with one hand holds forth a Sword, even over Believers, to ſlay their Body, it ſmites one and other, <hi>hip and thigh;</hi> But obſerve its other hand, &amp; with that death opens a door of glory. Who would think that Death ſhould do this? 'Tis as in <hi>Sampſons</hi> riddle,
<note place="margin">Edulium ex edente.</note> 
               <hi>out of the eater came meat,</hi> it is a riddle indeed, but a very truth. And whereas Death is diſmal and dreadful, <hi>the King of fears,</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes now an <hi>Anchor of hope, the valley of Berachah or bleſſing;</hi> So that the Saints can welcome it, and ſay as <hi>David</hi> of <hi>Ahimaas, He is a good Man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.27.</note> 
               <hi>and bringeth good tidings.</hi> They can wait for it, <hi>Job</hi> 14.14. He was an expectant all his dayes, yea wiſh, for it, thus <hi>Paul, I deſire to be diſſolved,</hi> Phil. 1.23. They can ſtand as <hi>Abraham,</hi> in the door of the Tabernacle, to ſpeak to the Angel, or with <hi>Elijah,</hi> in the mouth of the cave to meet the Lord coming to them by death; Now how comes this to paſs? even becauſe they know they muſt be as it were beholding to Death, to do them this favour and kindneſs, to bring them to their bleſſedneſs. This ſure affords ſtrong Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Children of God.</p>
            <p>I ſhall carry on this uſe of Conſolation a little further, to the particular caſe of any who may be excerciſed in the loſs of godly Friends, <hi>they die in the Lord, and therefore are bleſſed.</hi> But you will ſay, this was matter of comfort concerning thoſe who dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under that perſecution to which this relates: But mark, the voice
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119077:19"/>from Heaven ſaid, <hi>Write,</hi> intimating it is of uſe in all ages, for what is written is for the Churches Learning and comfort to the end of the World: Bleſſed are the dead that die <hi>now</hi> in the Lord. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.4. Holds forth this bleſſedneſs which Saints ſhall have after this life is done, &amp; makes it a main argument of comfort to thoſe that ſurvive, having loſt their godly friends, verſe 18. <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore comfort one another with theſe words,</hi> and chiefly with the words immediately preceding, that they are dead in Chriſt, and ſo <hi>ſhall ever be with the Lord.</hi> This is comfort indeed, and it is but ſorry comfort where this hope is not fixed ſure: this foundation and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, will bear up the building of comfort.</p>
            <p>Heathens indeed who knew nothing of the bleſſedneſs of ſuch as die in Chriſt, had their conſolatory addreſſes to their afflicted Friends: They would tell them, Death was that which none could avoid, therefore in vain it was to grieve:
<note place="margin">Mors ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma linea rerum.</note> They told them it was the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon lot of all things; Not onely Men, but famous Cities, flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Kingdoms had their periods: <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> comforted himſelf at the death of his Children, ſaying, <hi>he begat them but mortal ones:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heri vidi fragilem ftangi, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diè morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem mori.</note> 
               <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pictetus</hi> ſeeing a Woman weeping for her pitcher which ſhe had broken, and next day for her Son being dead, ſtayed her mourning, telling her it was all one: her Son was but as an earthen pitcher.</p>
            <p>Little better are thoſe comforts wherewith carnal Chriſtians la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to relieve themſelves and their Friends in theſe caſes, as thus; <hi>Death is the way of all the earth, the houſe appointed for all living:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſh. 23.14. Job 30.23. Pſalm 119.109. Jam. 4.14. Iſa 40.6.</note> 
               <hi>we carry our lives in our hand: Our life is as a vapour, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth for a little time, and then vaniſheth away: All fleſh is graſs, and the goodlineſſe thereof as the flower of the field, the graſs withereth, the flower fadeth.</hi> Theſe are Scripture-truths indeed, and not taken out of Heathen Philoſophers or Poets: They are ſuch as rightly uſed and applyed, may be comfortable to relieve under the loſſe of Friends and dear relations; But their intendment is not ſo much for Conſolation as for Inſtruction to us, that hearing of the frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this life, we may prepare for eternity. Nor indeed in themſelves abſolutely can they afford any ſolid comfort, becauſe they ſpeak onely to the condition and ſtate of the Body; But when the ſtate of the Soul after Death comes to be weighed,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.10. Rev. 20.12 John 3.3, Rev. 20 10 Pſal. 9.17.</note> as <hi>that all muſt appear before the judgement ſeat of Chriſt, and that the Books ſhall be opened, and great and ſmall muſt ſtand before God:</hi> when it ſhall be conſidered that unleſs <hi>a Man be born again, he ſhall never ſee the Kingdom of God:</hi> when hear <hi>of the lake that burns with fire
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119077:20"/>and brimſtone, and that the wicked ſhall be turned into Hell.</hi> I ſay again, when theſe things come to be weighed, the other paſſages barely conſidered, will be but as a <hi>spiders web</hi> wherein is no ſtrength, how finely ſoever it may ſeem to be woven. But now when we have good grounds to believe concerning our dead Friends, that they loved, feared, and ſerved God in their life time, that they were godly, in Chriſt Jeſus, or in the words of the Text, that they were <hi>in the Lord Jeſus when they dyed,</hi> when we can <hi>comfort one another with theſe words,</hi> This will afford ſtrong conſolation, for of ſuch the word of truth ſaith, <hi>they are bleſſed;</hi> They are freed from ſin, made perfect in holineſs, they are entred into their Maſters joy, they would not live again on earth, they are ten thouſand thouſand times better: This is comfort indeed, this is an Handkerchief to wipe away all tears from our eyes, yea, to make us <hi>go away and be no more ſad.</hi> This is the uſe of Conſolation; Oh that Chriſtians would lay it up as a choice treaſure, for ſo indeed it is; Some may need it for the preſent, let them make uſe of it; Others may ſoon need it, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore lay it up againſt a time of need: 'Tis ordinary with us when we find any thing, though for the preſent we know not what uſe to put it to, yet we will lay it up, ſaying, we may need it before ſeven years come about; So I ſay of this, you will ere long, one and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, have need of this cordial, therefore keep it by you carefully: you may need it before ſeven years come about, perhaps before ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven dayes, yea, ſeven hours come about: God may call you your ſelves to die, and what will be your comfort in a ſick bed, but to know you are in Chriſt, and ſo ſhall be bleſſed if you die? He may ſpare you and take away your Friends, Relations, wherein can you comfort your ſelves under ſuch providences but onely in this, they were in Chriſt, and therefore are bleſſed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth and laſt uſe ſhall be for Exhortation: It directs it ſelf both to Saints and Sinners: But a word to the firſt, becauſe there is great need of ſpeaking a little more largely to the other. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let all the Children of God, and Members of Chriſt, ſtudy their own bliſs, &amp; acquaint the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves before hand with the glory that ſhall be revealed <hi>afterwards.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Surſum corda.</note> 
               <hi>Set your affections on things above; Let your converſation be in Heaven:</hi> Labour in your meditations to be <hi>rapt up into the third Heaven:</hi> Be often as it were drawing the Latch of Heaven door, and look in, yea, <hi>walk thorough that holy Land in the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119077:20"/>length and breadth of it:</hi> Holy, Heavenly Meditations will enable you to do all this. Let your hearts take poſſeſſion of Heaven whiles your bodies are upon earth, and this will work a diſdain of things below,
<note place="margin">Non ſatis futura gaudia, noſtri niſi renuat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolari anima tua donec ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niant.</note> as alſo a longing after the things above, which ought to be in every Child of God: ſurely the more we ſtudy this bleſſedneſs, the more will the deſire after it be kindled in our breaſts.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall ſpeak no more to this part of the uſe, becauſe all a long, and eſpecially in the foregoing uſe, I have ſpoken to this matter in particular. Therefore</p>
            <p n="2">2. This uſe directs it ſelf to ſuch as are yet ſinners, out of Chriſt; My Exhortation to you is this, that you would ſpeedily get into Chriſt: That you would labour to be ſuch, as that when you come to die, you may be bleſſed: Die you muſt. <hi>Zerxes</hi> that great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandre, ſtanding in the head of a vaſt Army, wept to think that within one hundred years they would be all dead, even thoſe valo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Men, who might ſeem to outbrave and defie death; The im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility to avoid death is a certain truth at all times, but yet chiefly to be conſidered by us in theſe dying times, times of much mortality, <hi>God putting us in fear, that we may know our ſelves to be but Men,</hi> Pſal. 9.20. We are apt to <hi>put far away the evil day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 6.3. Iſa. 28.15</note> 
               <hi>and to make Covenants with death;</hi> but when we ſtudy ſeriouſly the decree of God paſſing upon all, like the Laws of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> which cannot be altered; when we conſider our own weakneſs and frailty, our mould and metal, we cannot but know we muſt die: If our inſide were turned outward, it would be ſeen that for fear of death, we are <hi>all our life time ſubject to bondage:</hi> This lyes near our breaſt,
<note place="margin">Heb. 2.15.</note> and makes the heart even die within us, while yet we live.</p>
            <p>Oh poor Sinners! die you muſt, and no doubt but you would be glad to be bleſſed when you die; <hi>Balaam</hi> would fain be happy in death, <hi>Let me die the death of the righteous,</hi> Numb. 23.10. His wiſh implies, that none ſhall be bleſſed in death but the righteous:
<note place="margin">Sic mihi contingat vivere, ſic<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mori. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Now would you be happy in death, be holy in life: live in the Lord, and you ſhall die in the Lord: If you be gracious here, you ſhall be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious hereafter: <hi>To whom to live is Chriſt, to them to die will be gain;</hi> But to them who live without Chriſt and without holineſs, <hi>Death will be Death, and Hell into the bargain.</hi> 'Tis a frequent and true ſaying, that holineſs is the way to happineſs, not the cauſal and meritorious way, which onely is Chriſt, but yet a <hi>way,</hi> and therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Ep.</hi> 2.10. That <hi>God hath ordained that we ſhould walk in it,</hi> that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119077:21"/>wherein we are to walk, certainly is a way, and if any baulk holineſs the way, they will never find happineſs the end: 'Tis ſaid of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Baſſianus,</hi> that coming to the Empire, and being to chuſe a Title, he was wiſhed by one to take the name of <hi>Pius,</hi> which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies Godly, but he refuſing that, choſe rather to be called <hi>Faelix,</hi> which ſignifies happy, which occaſioned his Friend to make this wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty reply, <hi>and doth the Emperour think to be happy without being holy?</hi> 'Tis much diſputed where the place of happineſs is, and divers opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions are about it, but it is agreed on all hands about, which is the way that leads to it: The way is but one in this ſenſe, the way of Holineſs, which is not onely but one way, but alſo a ſtraight and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row way, oppoſed to all looſe and ſinful walkings: Heaven is a place which receives not the proud, but the humble, not the covetous, but the liberal, not the unclean, but the chaſte, not the drunken, but the ſober, not the envious and malicious, but ſuch as are of a meek,
<note place="margin">Col. 1.12. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>qui idoneos nos fecit. Trem.</hi> Beza.</note> gentle, and loving Spirit: <hi>'Tis the inheritance of Saints,</hi> for which perſons muſt be <hi>made meet or fitted:</hi> The Spirit of God finds perſons ſinful, but it new moulds them, and changeth them into holy ones before it brings them to Heaven.</p>
            <p>'Tis ſaid of one of the Roman Emperours, when he came to the Empire, he found the City built of Brick, but before he dyed, their buildings were of Marble: I may apply it to the change which the Holy Ghoſt makes in the Soul,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Invenit lateritiam, reliquit marmor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eam.</hi> Suet. <hi>in vit.</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt.</note> he makes a ſinful Soul holy, which is more then to pull down buildings of Brick, and to erect buildings of marble: The reſult of all is this, that Holines is the way to bleſſedneſs, they who would take Chriſt for a Saviour, muſt take him for a Sampler: they who would have the benefit of his death, muſt take the example of his life. The Exhortation therefore is, labour to be holy, as ever you deſire to be happy; Be divorced from your luſts, caſt away your idols, ſubdue the ſtrength of ſin, bid no welcome to the Friends of ſin, watch againſt the wiles and fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of ſin: make you a clean heart, get a regenerate heart, the image of God renewed upon your Souls,
<note place="margin">Qui vult finem, vult media ad finem.</note> ceaſe not till you be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of the Divine Nature. In a word, be godly in Chriſt Jeſus: you muſt uſe the means in order to the deſired end: <hi>Muſt go to the School of Grace, before you can come to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall now lay down 4. things by way of caution, and then a few cloſing Counſels, and ſo I will have done. For the cautions.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:119077:21"/>
            <p n="1">1. Do not think that all ſhall be bleſſed, for onely they ſhall be bleſſed, who are in the Lord when they die: To be in Chriſt, and to be godly is all one: Now the Scripture ſaith, not onely that all are not godly, but that the number of godly ones, compared with the ungodly, is but ſmall, abſolutely conſidered they are many, <hi>Matthew</hi> 8.11. <hi>Many ſhall come and ſit down with Abraham, &amp;c.</hi> Revel. 7.4. <hi>An hundred and forty and four thouſand were ſealed:</hi> But comparatively they are but few, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.14. <hi>Narrow is the way that leadeth unto life, and few there be that find it,</hi> Luke 12.32. <hi>Fear not little flock,</hi> or as the Original will bear, <hi>little,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle flock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Do not think that Chriſt and grace, and a right to bleſſedneſs may be had when thou wilt, to be at thy beck, <hi>come and it comes:</hi> There is this preſumptuous conceipt in many, which makes them not ſo much as look after getting into Chriſt, till they come to die, when they have extreme need of being in Chriſt, and not to have Chriſt then to get:
<note place="margin">Luke 19.42.</note> Let Sinners hear and fear that word and wiſh of Chriſt, <hi>Oh that thou hadſt known in this thy day, the things that concern thy peace!</hi> yea, but they might ſay, we will know them, tis yet all in good time. He anſwers they had loſt their day and ſeaſon, and now they were hidden from their eys. Will not ſome bemoan themſelves when it is too late in the words of the Prophet?
<note place="margin">Jer. 8.20.</note> 
               <hi>The Summer is paſt, the Harveſt is ended, and we art not ſaved:</hi> The time of grace ends with the time of life to all. <hi>Manna</hi> muſt be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered on the ſix dayes of thy life, there is no gathering on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, reſembling thy reſt in death; <hi>there is no deviſe nor knowledge in the grave;</hi> But yet the day of grace may end with ſome, before they come to the end of the days of their life; And though we know not the expiration of it, nor can ſay of any particular perſon, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particular perſon ſay of himſelf, that the day of grace is paſt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it were known that he had ſinned the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt; Yet Scripture expreſſions hold forth the truth of the thing, that it is ſo; And therefore let all preſumptuous delayers look well about them, and O Sinner, to day, on this thy day hear the voice of Chriſt, <hi>believe and repent.</hi> How knoweſt thou but this may be the day, this the Sermon, which if thou rejecteſt, Mercy and Peace may be for ever hidden from thine eyes. Bleſſedneſs is not to be had when thou wilt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Do not think, though thou liveſt in ſin, and <hi>goeſt on in thy wickedneſſe,</hi> yet thou mayeſt come to Heaven at laſt for all that;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119077:22"/>Conſider, and ſeriouſly weigh but theſe Scriptures, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.19. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9. And if this have been thy thought, thy inward thought, (for none will ſay ſo, whatever they think) they may well make thee be of another mind.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And laſtly, by way of caution, think not that every remiſs way of ſerving of God, will ſerve the turn to bring thee to bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: Lukewarmneſs is the ſin of our age, and the bane of our Souls; Many Chriſtians by profeſſion, are in their ſpiritual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,
<note place="margin">1 King 2.1.</note> like <hi>David</hi> in his old age as to his bodily condition, ſo cold, that <hi>though they covered him with cloathes, yet he gat no heat;</hi> All the Ordinances under which they lie, will not warm them into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Zeal, but they continue either very cold and frozen, or at moſt but lukewarm; Like the Climat wherein they live, which is neither extreme cold, nor violently hot, but temperate; they have a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, but no power, they keep in a round of duties, without being quickned in any love to God, or zeal for God; but alaſs this will not bring to Bleſſedneſs, as was ſhewed before in the opening of the Text. Theſe are the cautions.</p>
            <p>Now to draw to a Concluſion, I have from the Scripture before us, held forth the bliſs and happineſs of Saints, and thereby an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer hath been made of the ſame bleſſedneſs unto Sinners: It offers it ſelf to you, Oh that you would offer your ſelves to it! In this Sermon you may ſay, <hi>Salvation came to your Houſe:</hi> it came to your Doors; Heaven goes a begging that it may be accepted; But it fares in this caſe, as we commonly obſerve in other caſes, proffer'd things find little acceptance, becauſe proffered: And indeed if we conſider the multitude of Sermons that are preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and how in every Sermon Chriſt, and Heaven, and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs are offered, yet by very few accepted; We muſt needs think and judge, the frequent tenders do through the corruption of our hearts, occaſion the horrible ſleighting of them: Silver in the days of <hi>Solomon;</hi> being common was of no account: The Lord grant this ſin bring not upon us the ſcarcity of the Word, that it ſhould be with us as in the dayes of <hi>Samuel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>The Word of the Lord was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in thoſe dayes, there was no open viſion.</hi> The time may come, when we would give a world to ſee one of the dayes of the Son of Man, and ſhall not ſee it: To hear one Sermon of Heaven and glory, but ſhall not hear it.</p>
            <p>I have ſhewed Saints the bleſſedneſs which they ſhall have, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119077:22"/>to Sinners the way how they may ſhare in this Bleſſedneſſe: I do again counſel Sinners to look after it, yea, in the Name of the Lord I charge you to cloſe with it; Now to provoke you to it, I ſhall lay down five cloſing Concluſions very briefly, and ſo leave them upon your hearts and thoughts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This Counſel is ſuch as never any repented that took it: It worketh repentance not to be repented of; If any repent of Chriſt, it is becauſe he never truly knew Chriſt: They who ſay, <hi>it is in vain to ſerve God,</hi> Malachi 3.4. Are ſuch as never truly ſerved him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis ſuch Counſel, as if it be refuſed, you will certainly repent of the refuſal, yea, and that when it is too late: Oh that I had known the things of my peace! will be the doleful lamentation in the ſcorching flames of Hell.</p>
            <p n="3">3. 'Tis ſuch Counſel as in your own Conſciences, when you are ſerious, you think you ought to take; Yea, Sinners think to do it, whereby they ſhew that they know, they ought to do it;
<note place="margin">Fertur e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui Auriga</note> The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why it is not done, is not becauſe we do not know it ought to be done, but we are hurried with our ſtrong luſts and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; We are cumbred with our Farmes and our Trades, we looſe Heaven in the crowd of earthly buſineſſes.</p>
            <p n="4">4. 'Tis ſuch Counſel, as if followed, carries its reward with it, though there were no Bleſſedneſs to enſue, no glory afterwards: ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs is happineſs, Gods work is wages.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And laſtly, the contempt of it will not onely leave you ſhort of Bleſſedneſſe, but conclude you under inevitable miſery and curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe, it will bring an heavy ſhock of wrath and ruine upon Soul and Body.</p>
            <p>Hear the Concluſion of the whole matter; <hi>Get into Chriſt,</hi> for this will free you from being curſed, and alſo make you everlaſtingly Bleſſed.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:119077:23"/>
            <head>CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Sermon preſented to your view, was preached at the Funeral of Mr. <hi>Thomas Goodwyn,</hi> an eminent light and pillar of the Church in the place where he lived, who <hi>after he had ſerved his generation by the Will of God, fell on ſleep, Sept.</hi> 4. 1658.</p>
            <p>He ſleeps in Jeſus; he gave evident proof that he was one in Chriſt, and therefore we may conclude from what hath been ſpoken, he is now Bleſſed, for <hi>bleſſed are the dead that die in the Lord,</hi> or that are in the Lord when they die: He was a good, yea, a precious Man: Let him have the <hi>memorial of the righteous, which is and ſhall be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> He was well known to be a Miniſter of great worth, every way qualified for the work of the Miniſtery: It was his deſire from a Youth to be a Miniſter (as himſelf hath ſometimes told me) &amp; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his hearts deſire, the Lord in due time diſpoſed of him, and drew him out to that ſervice, fitting him for it, and bleſſing him in it. How he was fitted for it, the Brethen in the whole County, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others to whom he was known in more remote places, will give ample Teſtimony.</p>
            <p>How he was bleſſed in it, the many weeping eyes at his Funeral, with the ſad complaints ſtill under this great loſs do ſpeak: theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare him to have been under God an inſtrument of much good. Though ſucceſs do not conſtitute a good Miniſtery (for a good Man may <hi>fiſh all night and catch nothing,</hi>) yet it doth declare and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence it: Theſe I remember were his own words, long ſince in the time of his health at the Lecture in <hi>Brentwood,</hi> and this evidence he abundantly had.</p>
            <p>He was learned and godly,
<note place="margin">Doctior an Sanctior?</note> which is a moſt bleſſed conjunction, where ever they meet; it is hard to ſay which of the two did bear
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119077:23"/>the preeminence in him, they ſeemed to keep pace, and that no ſlow pace; He was eminent in both. He had much profited in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Learning, but eſpecially in the ſtudies of Divinity, and in particular had gotten great acquaintance with the Scriptures; He was like <hi>Ezra, A ready Scribe in the Law of God, he was an.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezr. 7.6. Acts 18.24.</note> 
               <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los, mighty in the Scriptures.</hi> He was but young, yet his attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were very great, God gave of his Spirit abundantly to him. In Praying he was a ſweet Soul, full of the breathings of the Holy Ghoſt: In Preaching he was very powerful, ſpeaking to his Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers as if he had been within them: In his walking he was an Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary Chriſtian, an Exemplary Miniſter, he might ſay to his people, as <hi>Gideon</hi> to his Souldiers, <hi>Look on me, and do likewiſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jud. 7.17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>His Preaching was ſuch, that the godly learned did admire him, and yet the meaneſt capacities (they of the Belfry, as is Mr. <hi>Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi>'s expreſſion) did underſtand him; he had ſuch a winning way, that his Sermons were not tedious, but his Hearers ſeemed to be chained to his lips.</p>
            <p>He was a great Pains-taker; in preaching ſo often, and yet carried on with delight: I am perſwaded, he might have ſaid in the words of that holy Biſhop, <hi>My witneſs is in Heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cowper.</note> 
               <hi>that the love of Chriſt, and peoples Souls, made frequent Preaching my recreation and pleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Words ſeemed to come from his very heart, one that did <hi>eat the roll,</hi> as the Prophet is bid,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 3.1.</note> before he gave it to his Hearers to digeſt: An Argument that they <hi>came from the heart,</hi> was his earneſt driving on, that they might <hi>go to the hearts</hi> of his people; He thought he had done nothing, till his Hearers hearts were more renewed, and their Lives more reformed: Till (to uſe his own words) <hi>he could read the Sabbath-dayes work, in their Week-dayes converſation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Life was a looking-glaſs, wherein the people might ſee to dreſſe and attire their Converſation: I may ſay in the words of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.10. <hi>His people were Witneſſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ille ſolus praedicat vivâ voce, qui praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat vitâ &amp; voce.</note> 
               <hi>and God alſo; how holily, and juſtly, and unblamably, he behaved himſelf among them:</hi> being as a Miniſter of Chriſt ought to be, <hi>a lover of good Men, ſober, juſt, holy, temperate,</hi> Tit. 1.8.</p>
            <p>He was very zealous in the work of Reformation: The zeal of Gods Houſe did even eat him up, and in the cauſe of God he
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119077:24"/>ſhewed undaunted Courage, vigorouſly purſuing what might make for the glory of God, in deſpite of all oppoſition; one might ſtand upon his grave, and ſay as a great perſon ſaid over the grave of Mr. <hi>Knox, Here lies one who never feared the Face of any Man.</hi> I knew him well, yet could I never perceive that he was ſinfully, and proudly puffed up, though his large endowments might have tempted him thereunto, but in his whole Converſation, as far I could judge, did behave himſelf holily, humbly.</p>
            <p>He lived free from worldly Encombrances, but very full of cares for the promoting Gods glory, and his peoples Salvation: He hath ſometime told me in the time of his health, how ſadly it would go to his heart, (upon hearing the Bell ring ſometime in the night, which gave notice that ſome perſon was dead) that any one ſhould be ſick and die, and himſelf their Paſtor have no notice of their ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, nor be ſo much as deſired to confer with them about their ſpiritual eſtate: His Lamentation was in theſe words, <hi>Moriuntur oves, dormitat Pastor,</hi> The ſhepheard lies a ſleeping, while the ſheep lie adying. The great care of Souls made him ſtudy how to quit himſelf from being overcharged with the cares of this life, declaring by his little medling with the things of the world, that he <hi>ſought not the things of his own, but the things of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> This ſhould be the endeavour of every ſincere Chriſtian, but eſpecially of every faithful Miniſter.</p>
            <p>The Palm Tree,
<note place="margin">Pſalm 92.12.</note> to which the righteous is compared, is leaſt in the body or trunk near the earth, and biggeſt in the boughs neareſt Heaven: The frame of the fleſhly heart in the body being cloſe ſhut up in that part which is towards the earth, but more broad and open in the upper part towards Heaven, ſhewes what ſhould be the ſpiritual frame of every gracous heart: Thus was it with this good Man,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.4</note> and precious Servants of Jeſus Chriſt, he abhorred to be <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled with the affairs of this life,</hi> that Heaven might have the more room in his heart.</p>
            <p>In a word, He was a Miniſter of the Goſpel, and he did, <hi>Hoc agere,</hi> endeavour the fulfilling of his Miniſtery; He did intend his work, he made it his buſineſſe, being one who <hi>ſtudied to approve himſelf to God, a Work-man that needed not to be aſhamed,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.15.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:119077:24"/>
            <p>He was taken away young, but he <hi>did work while it was day,</hi> yea, he laboured much, as if he did foreſee, he had not long time to work in: <hi>Diu vixit, et ſi non diu fnit,</hi> He did much work in a little time. 'Tis much to be lamented that his Sermon notes were written ſo illegibly, through a quick and haſty writing, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it becomes impoſſible, they ſhould ever be publiſhed to the glory of God, and the benefit of the Church.</p>
            <p>Thus have I given a brief account of what he was in the time of his Life and Health: Divers know what hath been ſpoken, is no other than what might be ſpoken deſervedly and in truth; yea, much more might be ſpoken without any ſuſpicion of Flattery. The ſumme of all is this, <hi>He lived in the Lord, he lived to the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I may add, <hi>He died in the Lord, yea, died to the Lord,</hi> as may be judged by his deportment under that ſickneſſe which ended his dayes: <hi>Dying to the Lord</hi> as hath been ſhewed, is when a perſon caſt upon his ſick bed endeavours the exerciſe and laying out of his graces to the glory of God, and the profit of them with whom he doth converſe: Thus did he very ſweetly, ſo far as could poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be expreſſed, conſidering the ſhortneſſe of his ſickneſſe, being but for the ſpace of fourteen dayes, as I beſt remember, and the Stupifyingneſſe of his Diſeaſe, ſeizing and much dulling his Spirits.</p>
            <p>He did much impair the ſtrength of his outward Man, by a free letting out himſelf in diſcourſe about Heavenly things to ſome Neighbours, who came to viſit him, the firſt Sabbath after he was taken: This did much increaſe his diſtempers, and of this he was the day following very ſenſible, and could not but confeſſe it to me, at my firſt viſiting of him; At this my firſt viſit, in diſcourſe I ſpake to him by way of remembrance, if need were, about that Chriſtian duty of willing ſubmiſion to Gods Will, under every diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of providence, and ſo that of his preſent ſickneſs in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular: To this counſel he readily concurred, and withal added, <hi>that it was his deſire to reach further, and not onely to ſubmit, which an ordinary Chriſtian might do, but to raiſe up himſelf to Courage and Cheerfulneſſe under the rod;</hi> Annexing alſo a reaſon, why he of all Men ſhould not droop under Affliction, ſaying, <hi>he bleſſed God, that hitherto he could date his choiſeſt mercies from ſome great Affliction.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:119077:25"/>
            <p>I ſometime in diſcourſe, held forth what deſperate attempts Satan had made upon Gods Children, when they were brought low by ſickneſſe, and therefore counſelled him to ſet Faith on work, being the onely Shield to quench the fiery darts of the Devil: To this he replyed, that <hi>I bleſſe God, as yet, Satan hath got no ground by this Affliction.</hi> This paſſed, I think at a ſecond viſit. But comming to him again after a few dayes, (it was on the Sabbath day, the laſt Sabbath to him in this life,) I found him brought low by his ſickneſſe, inſomuch that I then began to fear he would not break it: Hereupon I entred a more cloſe diſcourſe as to eternity, hinting withal my own fears, that his ſickneſſe might be mortal, he took it (as he expreſſed himſelf) exceeding kindly, and gave me a full Anſwer to what in my diſcourſe I drove at. <hi>Dear Friend,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>two dayes ſince I overheard the Doctor ſpeaking to my Wife, as if he feared me: and I bleſſe God who ſo ordered it that I ſhould hear it: For indeed till then, I did not ſo ſeriouſly conſider of death, as ſince I have done; I did all a long my ſickneſs ſet my heart to endeavour a ſanctified uſe of the Lords hand, but overhearing that, I thought it needful to look moſt carefully into my heart, as to evidences for eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and truly,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>upon a thorough ſearch of my heart, I bleſſe God, I find good old evidences, though I be but a young Man, and they ſtick very cloſe to me: But Friend,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>one thing I must tell you troubles and afflicts my Spirit very much, that when I grew very ſerious, being exerciſed about ſerious work, the ſearching of my heart for eternity evidences, I perceived this ſeriouſneſs of mine, was judged by ſome to be melancholy for the fear of death: Now this indeed troubles me very much, that any ſhould take me to be ſuch an one, who am afraid to die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some other viſits I gave him, but for fear of wronging him being very weak; I onely upon his deſire prayed with him and left him: At one of theſe times he ſpake privately to me, that he was willing to have diſcourſed, but becauſe of ſome Company in the room, he judged it not convenient.</p>
            <p>Upon <hi>Fryday,</hi> the day before he departed, I had ſome diſcourſe with him, which was occaſioned thus: Some godly Neighbours had agreed a private meeting to ſeek the Lord for him, and they had deſired me to meet with them: Now that I might know the better how to order my Petitions, I thought it needful to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119077:25"/>viſit my ſick Friend in the way, and therby to be better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, whether his ſickneſſe did increaſe upon him; I came to his Bed-ſide, but he layſtil, and ſeemed not to know me: Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon his Wife asked him if he knew me, he ſaid yes, and called me by my name; but withall asked if it were <hi>Thurſday,</hi> (ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing I had been come to the Lecture, and ſo by the way viſited him:) I then told him it was <hi>Fryday,</hi> and ſo gave him an account whither I was going, even to joyn with his people in ſeeking the Lord for him, and deſired to know, what he would have us moſt importune the Lord for on his behalf.</p>
            <p>After a little pauſe, he brake out into moſt affectionate ſpeeches, to expreſſe his own ſenſe of his peoples love to him, and how great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his Love was ſet upon them: I could not bear away all his words, but he was full of theſe, <hi>Oh my poor people! Oh the Souls of my poor people! How dear, how precious are they to me! Oh if God ſhould spare me, how would I lay out my ſelf for them! After this he prayed me to commend him to his people, and tell them, that wherein he deſired their prayers was to begg of God a clearer ſenſe of his love, ſaying, not that I altogether want it, for I bleſs God, I have it, but</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Sometimes</hi> — and ſo laid down and ſaid no more, and I finding him to be much ſpent with ſpeaking, durſt not urge him any further, but went away partly rejoycing that though Satan did buffet, yet that he had been able to prevail no further.</p>
            <p>On the next day being <hi>Saturday,</hi> (in the evening whereof the Lord took him) I went again to him in the afternoon, but before I was up the ſtairs, I heard him ſpeaking with a very loud voice; This at firſt hearing ſtruck my heart, perceiving his diſtemper was come to that height, that there could be no hopes conceived of his life: before I went in, I ſtood hearing him a little time at the door,
<note place="margin">Cygnea cantio. Oportet E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopum concionan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem mori.</note> and by and by went in, and ſtood by his bed-ſide, attending to what he ſpake; where indeed I heard a precious, powerful diſcourſe about the ſweetneſs &amp; fulneſs of Chriſt: It was ſpoken juſt as if he had been in the Pulpit preaching: I could not but ſtand and wonder to hear a diſtempered head vent ſuch a diſcourſe, ſo methodical and ſo clear, with the quoting of Scriptures, and no failing in ſenſe, and not much faultring in words; he quoted 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.21, 22, 23. And went as far as he could in rehearſing the words, <hi>All things are yours, whether Paul, or Apollos, or Cephas, or the world, or life, or death,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119077:26"/>or things</hi> — here his mouth being much clam'd he could not get out his words, but yet made a ſhift to add, <hi>becauſe ye are Chriſts:</hi> I know the diſtemper of his head was the cauſe of this loud ſpeech, but yet I believe this diſtemper was a means to draw forth what was in his heart. Now perceiving that he had ſpent himſelf far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond what his then little or no ſtrenth would bear, I ſpake to him ſaying; My dear Friend, though your diſcourſe may be very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to my ſelf and others that ſtand by, yet I know it doth much ſpend and weaken you, and ſo wiſhed him to forbear and lie ſtill; Hereupon he did ceaſe a while, and after ſome little pauſe, he ſpake again in ſome few, (but very ſweet words,) which were theſe; <hi>Well, it is a ſweet thing when he that speaks of Chriſt, hath Chriſt dwelling in him at that time when he ſpeaks.</hi> After this he ſpake no more while I was there, neither can I learn of others that he ſpake any more, but left thoſe for his laſt words: And ſo falling into ſlumbrings and cold ſweats before midnight, he gave up the Ghoſt. He had fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhed his Teſtimony; The Witneſſes cannot be ſlain till this be done, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.7. His work was done, and now he hath his Crown; Our work is not yet done, but it remains that we be followers of the Saints, as they were followers of Chriſt, then ſhall we alſo <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Crown,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>the Crown of righteouſneſs which the Lord, the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judge ſhall give,</hi> not to a <hi>Paul</hi> only, a Miniſter, a Preacher of the Goſpel; <hi>But to them alſo that love his appearing.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
